<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of Quantum Private Information Retrieval with Multiple Servers</title>
				<funder ref="#_cx3QChu">
					<orgName type="full">Kyoto University, Japan</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_rkfbd38">
					<orgName type="full">JSPS</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_N69aqpm">
					<orgName type="full">Kayamori Foundation of Information Science Advancement</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_vBuVgUx">
					<orgName type="full">Nagoya University</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_q3dSbyW">
					<orgName type="full">Lotte Foundation Scholarship</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Japan Academy</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_ZCZ4QuY #_wBr9HHy #_kHrn5xF">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">MEXT) Graduate School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_B5KZyfK">
					<orgName type="full">JSPS Prize from Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Faculty of Sciences in Kyoto University, Japan</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_3uGkkwr">
					<orgName type="full">Shenzhen Institute for Quantum Science and Engineering, Southern University of Science and Technology, Shenzhen, China as Chief Research Scientist</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_VAX5qs5">
					<orgName type="full">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2021-01-20">20 Jan 2021</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Student Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Seunghoan</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Fellow, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Masahito</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
							<email>hayashi@sustech.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">school of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nagoya University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>464-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Nagoya</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Quantum Science and Engi- neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Shenzhen Institute for Quantum Science and Engi- neering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Southern University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518055</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<region>China</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Quantum Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southern University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518055</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Southern University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>518055</postCode>
									<settlement>Shenzhen</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Nagoya University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>464-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Nagoya</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of Quantum Private Information Retrieval with Multiple Servers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2021-01-20">20 Jan 2021</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EB0DF409F1AFE39A53572A1134869720</idno>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1903.10209v4[quant-ph]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T12:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We study the capacity of quantum private information retrieval (QPIR) with multiple servers. In the QPIR problem with multiple servers, a user retrieves a classical file by downloading quantum systems from multiple servers each of which contains the copy of a classical file set while the identity of the downloaded file is not leaked to each server. The QPIR capacity is defined as the maximum rate of the file size over the whole dimension of the downloaded quantum systems. When the servers are assumed to share prior entanglement, we prove that the QPIR capacity with multiple servers is 1 regardless of the number of servers and files. We construct a rate-one protocol only with two servers. This capacity-achieving protocol outperforms its classical counterpart in the sense of the capacity, server secrecy, and upload cost. The strong converse bound is derived concisely without using any secrecy condition. We also prove that the capacity of multi-round QPIR is 1.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Introduced by the seminal paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, Private Information Retrieval (PIR) finds efficient methods to download a file from non-communicating servers each of which contains the copy of a classical file set while the identity of the downloaded file is not leaked to each server. This problem is trivially solved by requesting all files to one of the servers, but this method is inefficient. Finding an efficient method is the goal of this problem and it has been extensively studied in many papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Moreover, the papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> have studied the Quantum PIR (QPIR) problem where the user downloads quantum systems instead of classical bits to retrieve a classical file from the servers.</p><p>In classical PIR studies, the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> started the discussion of the PIR capacity. The PIR capacity is defined by the maximum rate of the file size over the download size when the numbers of the servers and the files are fixed. In the definition of the PIR capacity, the upload cost, i.e., the total size of the queries, is neglected since it does not scale with the file size which is allowed to go infinity. When each of the n servers contains a copy of the f files, the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> showed that the PIR capacity is (1 -1/n)/(1 -(1/n) f ). Moreover, the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> proposed a capacity-achieving protocol with the minimum upload cost and minimum file size in a class of PIR protocols. Furthermore, after <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, several PIR capacities have been studied under different problem settings. Symmetric PIR is the PIR with server secrecy that the user obtains no more information than the target file, and the capacity of the symmetric PIR is 1n -1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Another extension is the PIR with coded databases <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, where the files are coded and distributed to the servers. When the files are coded by an (n, k) Maximum Distance Separable (MDS) code, the PIR capacity is (1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Multi-round PIR has also been studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and the capacity was proved to be the same as the PIR capacity derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">-k/n)/(1 -(k/n) f )</formula><p>On the other hand, the QPIR problem is rarely treated with multiple servers and there is no study on the capacity of the QPIR problem. Though the papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> treated the QPIR problem with multiple servers, they evaluated the communication complexity which is the sum of upload and download costs required to retrieve a one-bit file instead of the capacity.</p><p>In this paper, as quantum extensions of the classical PIR capacities <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, we show that the capacities of QPIR, symmetric QPIR, and multi-round QPIR are 1. We derive the QPIR capacity when a user retrieves a file secretly from non-communicating n servers each of which contains the whole set of f files by downloading quantum states under the assumption that an entangled state is shared previously among all servers. We evaluate the security of a QPIR protocol with three parameters: the retrieval error probability, the user secrecy that the identity of the queried file is unknown to any individual server, and the server secrecy that the user obtains no more information than the target file. As a main result, we show that the QPIR capacity is 1 regardless of whether it is of exact/asymptotic security and with/without the restriction that the upload cost is negligible to the download cost. We propose a rate-one QPIR protocol with perfect security and finite upload cost. We prove the converse bound that the rate of any QPIR protocol is less than 1 even with no secrecy, no upload constraint, and any error probability. Moreover, we show that the capacity of multi-round QPIR is 1. We prove the weak converse bound of the multi-round QPIR capacity, i.e., the upper bound when the error probability is asymptotically zero.</p><p>Our capacity-achieving protocol has several remarkable advantages compared to the protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> with the minimum upload cost and the minimum file size (see Table <ref type="table">I</ref>). First, our protocol is a symmetric QPIR protocol which guarantees the server secrecy, i.e., the user obtains no information of files other than the retrieved one. This contrasts with the protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> that retrieves some information of the other files. Secondly, our protocol keeps the secrecy against the malicious user and servers. That is, the user cannot obtain more information than the target file even if the user sends malicious queries to the servers, and the servers cannot obtain the identity of the user's target file even if the servers answer malicious file information. Thirdly, the rate 1 of our protocol is greater than the rate (1n -1 )/(1n -f ) of the protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Fourthly, our protocol achieves the capacity 1 only with two servers. That is, in the sense of the QPIR capacity, there is no benefit to using more than two servers. On the other hand, in the protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the capacity is strictly increasing in the number of servers and strictly decreasing in the number of files, and an infinite number of servers are needed to achieve the capacity 1. Fifthly, our protocol needs the upload of 2f bits whereas the protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> needs (n(f -1) log n)-bit upload. Lastly, our protocol is defined when the file size m is the square of any integer, but the protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> requires the file size m to be the (n -1)-th power of any integer.</p><p>The converse proofs of the QPIR capacities are much simpler than those of the PIR capacities <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Whereas the papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> used several entropic inequalities based on the assumptions on the PIR problem, our converse bounds are concisely derived without using any secrecy conditions but only by focusing on the download step of QPIR protocol.</p><p>It should be noted that our QPIR protocol can be considered as a distributed version of Oblivious Transfer (OT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. OT is equivalent to the symmetric PIR with one server and therefore, the symmetric PIR with multiple servers can be considered as a distributed version of OT. OT is an important cryptographic protocol because the free uses of an OT protocol construct an arbitrary secure multiparty computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. Unfortunately, the symmetric classical PIR cannot be constructed without shared randomness among servers <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. On the other hand, the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> showed that the two-way quantum communication between the user and the servers enables the symmetric PIR without shared randomness. Our result extends the result <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> so that the symmetric PIR can also be constructed without shared randomness even for the case of classical upload, quantum download, and prior entanglement among the servers. Note that if the quantum upload is allowed to our model, we do not need the assumption of the prior entanglement because the user can upload an entangled state to all servers.</p><p>We assume that the servers share an entangled state before the protocol starts, but do not communicate. Similarly, the prior entanglement by non-communicating multiple parties has been assumed in another quantum protocol, called Multiprover Quantum Interactive Proof (MQIP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. In MQIP, to solve a computational problem, a computationally-limited verifier sends queries to multiple provers who do not communicate with each other and have quantum computers, receives answers from them, and then verifies whether the answers from the provers give a correct solution of the problem. Similarly to our assumption, the MQIP studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> assumed that the provers share an entangled state before the protocol starts, but do not communicate with each other. However, even if the assumption of shared entanglement is similar, our communication model is different from those in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>: the papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> treated the quantum queries and quantum answers, and the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> treated the classical queries and classical answers, but our paper treats classical queries and quantum answers.</p><p>The remaining of this paper is organized as follows. Section II presents the formal definition of the QPIR protocol and the QPIR capacity and proposes the QPIR capacity theorem. Section III constructs the rate-one QPIR protocol and analyzes the security of our protocol against the malicious user and servers. Section IV proves the converse bound. Section V extends the result to the capacity of multi-round QPIR. Section VI is the conclusion of this paper.</p><p>Notations: For any set T , we denote by |T | the cardinality of the set T and by I T (or I) the identity operator on T . For any matrix B, we denote by B the complex conjugate of B and B † := B⊤ . The set of integers is denoted by Z, and User Target Index: K ∈ {1, . . . , f}</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">serv 1 W 1 W 2 . . . W f serv 2 W 1 W 2 . . . W f • • • serv n W 1 W 2 . . . W f Shared Entanglement ρ prev W K ∈ {0, . . . , m -1} Q 1 Q 2 Q n A 1 A 2 A n ρ W,Q Ã1 Ã2 Ãn</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. Quantum private information retrieval protocol with multiple servers.</p><p>The composite system of the servers is initialized to an entangled state ρperv.</p><p>Z d := Z/dZ for any integer d. Pr X [A] denotes the probability that the variable X satisfies the condition A. For any quantum system A, we denote the set of all quantum states on A by S(A).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. QPIR PROTOCOL AND MAIN THEOREM</head><p>In this section, we formally define the QPIR protocol and its capacity and presents the main theorem of the paper. For preliminaries on quantum information theory, see Appendix A.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Formal definition of QPIR protocol</head><p>In this paper, we consider the QPIR with multiple servers described as follows. Let n, f, m be integers greater than 1. The participants of the protocol are one user and n servers. The servers do not communicate with each other and each server contains the whole set of uniformly and independently distributed f files W 1 , . . . , W f ∈ {0, . . . , m -1}. Each server serv t possesses a quantum system Ãt and the n servers share an entangled state ρ prev ∈ S( n t=1 Ãt ). The user chooses the target file index K to retrieve the K-th file W K , where the distribution of K is uniform and independent of the files W 1 , . . . , W f .</p><p>To retrieve the W K , the user chooses a random variable R user in a set R user and encodes the queries by user encoder Enc user :</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Enc user (K, R user ) = (Q 1 , . . . , Q n ) ∈ Q 1 × • • • × Q n ,</formula><p>where Q t is the set of query symbols to the t-th server for any t ∈ {1, . . . , n}. The n queries Q 1 , . . . , Q n are sent to the servers serv 1 , . . . , serv n , respectively. After receiving the tth query Q t , each server serv t applies a Completely Positive Trace-Preserving (CPTP) map Λ t from Ãt to A t depending on Q t , W 1 , . . . , W f and sends the quantum system A t to the user. With the server encoder Enc serv t , the map Λ t is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Λ t = Enc serv t (Q t , W 1 , . . . , W f ),</formula><p>and the received state of the user is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">ρ W,Q := Λ 1 ⊗ • • • ⊗ Λ n (ρ prev ) ∈ S n t=1 A t ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where W := (W 1 , . . . , W f ) and Q := (Q 1 , . . . , Q n ). Next, the user retrieves the file W K by a decoder which is defined depending on K, Q as a Positive Operator-Valued Measure (POVM) Dec(K, Q) := {Y M } m M=0 . The protocol outputs the measurement outcome M ∈ {0, . . . , m} and if M = m, it is considered as the retrieval failure.</p><p>1) Protocol: When the numbers n and f of servers and files are fixed, a QPIR protocol of file size m is formulated by the 4-tuple Ψ (m) QPIR := (ρ prev , Enc user , Enc serv , Dec) of the shared entangled state ρ prev in the servers, the user encoder Enc user , the collection of the server encoders Enc serv := (Enc serv1 , . . . , Enc servn ), and the decoder Dec.</p><p>2) Security: For any t ∈ {1, . . . , n}, let user(Ψ (m) QPIR ) and serv t (Ψ (m) QPIR ) be the information of the user and the server serv t at the end of the protocol Ψ (m) QPIR , respectively. The security of a QPIR protocol Ψ (m) QPIR is evaluated by the error probability, the server secrecy, and the user secrecy defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">P err (Ψ (m) QPIR ) := Pr W,K,Q [M = W K ],<label>(2)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">S serv (Ψ (m) QPIR ) := I(W K c ; user(Ψ (m) QPIR )|K),<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">S user (Ψ (m) QPIR ) := max t∈{1,...,n} I(K; serv t (Ψ (m) QPIR )),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where I(•; •|•) denotes the conditional mutual information and</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">W K c := (W 1 , . . . , W K-1 , W K+1 , . . . , W f ). If S serv (Ψ<label>(m)</label></formula><p>QPIR ) = 0, the non-targeted files W K c are independent of the user information. Similarly, if S user (Ψ (m) QPIR ) = 0, the target file index K is independent of any individual server information.</p><p>3) Costs, rate, and capacity: Given a QPIR protocol Ψ (m) QPIR , we define the upload cost, the download cost, and the QPIR rate by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">U (Ψ (m) QPIR ) := n t=1 log |Q t |,<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">D(Ψ (m) QPIR ) := n t=1 log dim A t ,<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">R(Ψ (m) QPIR ) := log m D(Ψ (m) QPIR ) . (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">)</formula><p>The upload cost, the download cost, and the QPIR rate evaluate respectively the size of the whole query set</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Q 1 × • • • × Q n , the dimension of the downloaded quantum systems A 1 ⊗ • • •⊗ A n</formula><p>, and the efficnecy of the protocol. When the base of the logarithm is two, the QPIR rate means the number of retrieved bits per one qubit download. The QPIR capacity is the optimal QPIR rate when the numbers of servers and files are fixed, and we define it with constraints on the security parameters and upload cost. The asymptotic security-constrained capacity and the exact security-constrained capacity are defined with α ∈ [0, 1) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">β, γ, θ ∈ [0, ∞] by C α,β,γ,θ asymp := sup (8) lim inf ℓ→∞ R(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ), C α,β,γ,θ exact := sup (9) lim inf ℓ→∞ R(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ),</formula><p>where the supremum is taken for sequences {m ℓ } ∞ ℓ=1 such that lim ℓ→∞ m ℓ = ∞ and for sequences {Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">(m ℓ ) QPIR } ∞</formula><p>ℓ=1 of QPIR protocols to satisfy either <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> given by lim sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">ℓ→∞ P err (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ α, lim sup ℓ→∞ S serv (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ β, lim sup ℓ→∞ S user (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ γ, lim sup ℓ→∞ U (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) D(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ θ,<label>(8)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">P err (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ α, S serv (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ β, S user (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ γ, lim sup ℓ→∞ U (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) D(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ θ.<label>(9)</label></formula><p>It is trivial from the definition that for any α ∈ [0, 1) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">β, γ, θ ∈ [0, ∞], C 0,0,0,0 exact ≤ C α,β,γ,θ exact ≤ C α,β,γ,θ asymp ≤ C α,∞,∞,∞ asymp .<label>(10)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Main Result</head><p>The main theorem of this paper is given as follows.</p><p>Theorem II.1. When servers can share prior entanglement, the capacity of the quantum private information retrieval for f ≥ 2 files and n ≥ 2 servers is</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">C α,β,γ,θ exact = C α,β,γ,θ asymp = 1, for any α ∈ [0, 1) and β, γ, θ ∈ [0, ∞].</formula><p>Proof. In Sections III and IV, we will prove C 0,0,0,0 exact ≥ 1 and C α,∞,∞,∞ asymp ≤ 1 for any α ∈ [0, 1), respectively. Then, the inequality (10) implies the theorem.</p><p>Note that the capacity does not depend on the number of files f and the number of servers n. This contrasts with the classical PIR capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, which is strictly decreasing for f and strictly increasing for n. Moreover, the capacity does not depend on the security constraints, i.e., there is no trade-off between the capacity and the constraints α, β, γ, θ. Furthermore, the theorem implies that the symmetric QPIR capacity is 1.</p><p>Remark II.1. In our QPIR model, we assumed that the files W 1 , . . . , W n are uniformly random and mutually independent. However, the assumption is necessary only for proving the converse bounds. Without the assumption, our QPIR protocol has no error and achieves the perfect server and user secrecies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. CONSTRUCTION OF PROTOCOL</head><p>In this section, we construct a rate-one two-server QPIR protocol with the perfect security and negligible upload cost. Our protocol is constructed if the file size m is the square of an arbitrary integer ℓ. Then, by taking m ℓ = ℓ 2 , the sequence {Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">(m ℓ ) QPIR } ∞</formula><p>ℓ=1 of our protocols achieves the rate 1 with the perfect security and negligible upload cost, which implies</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">C 0,0,0,0 exact ≥ 1.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>In the following, we give preliminaries on quantum operations and states in Section III-A and construct the QPIR protocol in Section III-B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Preliminaries</head><p>For an arbitrary integer ℓ ≥ 2, let A be an ℓ-dimensional Hilbert space spanned by an orthonormal basis {|0 , . . . , |ℓ -1 }. Define a maximally entangled state |Φ on A ⊗ A by</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">|Φ := 1 √ ℓ ℓ-1 i=0 |i ⊗ |i .</formula><p>For a, b ∈ Z ℓ , the generalized Pauli operators on A are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">X := ℓ-1 i=0 |i + 1 i|, Z := ℓ-1 i=0 ω i |i i|,</formula><p>where ω = exp(2π √ -1/ℓ), and the discrete Weyl operators are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">W(a, b) := X a Z b = ℓ-1 i=0 ω ib |i + a i|.</formula><p>These operators satisfy the relations</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">Z b X a = ω ba X a Z b , W(a 1 , b 1 )W(a 2 , b 2 ) = ω b1a2 W(a 1 + a 2 , b 1 + b 2 ), W(a, b) † = ω ba W(-a, -b).</formula><p>For any matrix T := ℓ-1 i,j=0 t ij |i j| on A, we define the state |T in A ⊗ A by</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">|T := ℓ-1 i,j=0 t ij |i ⊗ |j .</formula><p>With this notation, the maximally entangled state is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">|Φ = (1/ √ ℓ)|I . Since T ⊤ = ℓ-1 i,j=0 t ij |j i|, it holds |T = (T ⊗ I)|I = (I ⊗ T ⊤ )|I . Moreover, for any unitaries U, V on A, we have (U ⊗ V)|T = |UTV ⊤ , (U ⊗ U)|I = |UU † = |I . (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_28">)</formula><p>With the basis given in the following proposition, we construct the measurement in our QPIR protocol.</p><p>Proposition III.1. The set</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">B := {(W(a, b) ⊗ I)|Φ | a, b ∈ Z ℓ } is an orthonormal basis of A ⊗ A.</formula><p>Proof. Since W(a, b) ⊗ I is a unitary matrix for any a, b ∈ Z ℓ , all elements in B are unit vectors. Then, it is sufficient to show that every different two vectors in B are mutually orthogonal:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">for any different (a, b), (c, d) ∈ Z 2 ℓ , ((W(a, b) ⊗ I)|Φ ) † (W(c, d) ⊗ I)|Φ = 0. (13) Since W(a, b) † W(c, d) = ω b(a-c) W(c-a, d-b</formula><p>), the left-hand side of ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">ω b(c-a) Φ|(W(c -a, d -b) ⊗ I)|Φ .</formula><p>Moreover, for any x, z ∈ Z ℓ , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">Φ|(W(x, z) ⊗ I)|Φ = 1 ℓ ℓ-1 i=0 i|W(x, z)|i (14) = 1 ℓ ℓ-1 i=0 ω iz i|i + x (15) = δ (x,z),(0,0)<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Thus, Eq. ( <ref type="formula">13</ref>) holds for any (a, b) = (c, d), which implies the desired statement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Rate-one QPIR protocol</head><p>In this section, we propose a rate-one two-server QPIR protocol with the perfect security and negligible upload cost. This protocol is constructed from the idea of the classical twoserver PIR protocol in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Section 3.1]</ref>.</p><p>In this protocol, a user retrieves a file W K from two servers serv 1 and serv 2 . Each server contains a copy of the files W 1 , . . . , W f ∈ {0, . . . , ℓ 2 -1 =: m ℓ -1} for an arbitrary integer ℓ. By identifying the set {0, . . . , ℓ 2 -1} with Z 2 ℓ , the files W 1 , . . . , W f are considered to be elements of Z 2 ℓ . We assume that serv 1 and serv 2 possess the ℓ-dimensional quantum systems A 1 and A 2 , respectively, and the maximally entangled state |Φ in A 1 ⊗ A 2 is shared at the beginning of the protocol.</p><p>1) Protocol: The QPIR protocol for retrieving W K is described as follows.</p><p>Step 1. Depending on the target file index K, the user chooses a subset R user of {1, . . . , f} uniformly. Let Q 1 := R user and</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">Q 2 := Q 1 \ {K} if K ∈ Q 1 , Q 1 ∪ {K} otherwise.</formula><p>Step 2. The user sends the queries Q 1 and Q 2 to serv 1 and serv 2 , respectively. Step 3.</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">serv 1 calculates H 1 := i∈Q1 W i ∈ Z 2</formula><p>ℓ and applies W(H 1 ) on the quantum system A 1 . Similarly, serv 2 calculates H 2 := i∈Q2 W i and applies W(H 2 ) to the quantum system A 2 . The state on</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">A 1 ⊗ A 2 is (W(H 1 ) ⊗ W(H 2 ))|Φ .</formula><p>Step 4. serv 1 and serv 2 send the quantum systems A 1 and A 2 to the user, respectively. Step 5. The user performs a POVM</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">Dec(K, Q) = {Y (a,b) | a, b ∈ Z ℓ } on the received state ρ W,Q , where each POVM ele- ment Y (a,b) for the outcome (a, b) is defined by Y (a,b) := (W(a, b) ⊗ I)|Φ Φ|(W(a, b) † ⊗ I) if K ∈ Q 1 , and Y (a,b) := (W(-a, -b) ⊗ I)|Φ Φ|(W(-a, -b) † ⊗ I)</formula><p>otherwise. The user obtains the measurement outcome (a, b) as the retrieval result.</p><p>2) Security: We analyze the security of the protocol, i.e., the error probability, the server secrecy, and the user secrecy.</p><p>The protocol has no error as follows. Note that</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">H 1 = H 2 + W K if K ∈ Q 1 , and H 1 = H 2 -W K otherwise. After Step 3, the state on A 1 ⊗ A 2 is W(H 1 ) ⊗ W(H 2 )|Φ = ω ∓bW K aH 2 √ ℓ (W(±W K ) ⊗ I)(W(H 2 ) ⊗ W(H 2 ))|I (17) = ω ∓bW K aH 2 √ ℓ (W(±W K ) ⊗ I)|I<label>(18)</label></formula><p>=</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">ω ∓bW K aH 2 (W(±W K ) ⊗ I)|Φ ,</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">H 2 = (a H2 , b H2 ) and W K = (a WK , b WK ) ∈ Z 2 ℓ . The equality (17) is derived from W(H 1 ) = W(±W K + H 2 ) = ω ∓bW K aH 2 W(±W K )W(H 2 )</formula><p>and the equality ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_37">18</ref>) is from <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. Therefore, in Step 5, the measurement outcome is</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">W K ∈ Z 2</formula><p>ℓ with probability 1. The perfect server secrecy is obtained because the received state (W(±W K ) ⊗ I)|Φ of the user is independent of the files W 1 , . . . , W K-1 , W K+1 , . . . , W f .</p><p>The perfect user secrecy follows from that of the protocol [1, Section 3.1]. Note that even if the collection of Q 1 and Q 2 depends on K, each of Q 1 and Q 2 is individually independent of the index K. Thus, the perfect user secrecy is obtained.</p><p>3) Upload cost, download cost, and rate: The upload cost is U (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) = 2f log 2 since two subsets Q 1 and Q 2 of {1, . . . , f} are uploaded and each subset of {1, . . . , f} is expressed by f bits. The download cost is D(Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">(m ℓ ) QPIR ) = log dim A 1 ⊗ A 2 = log ℓ 2 = log m ℓ . Therefore, the rate is R(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) = log m ℓ D(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) = 1,</formula><p>and U (Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">(m ℓ ) QPIR )/D(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) goes to zero as m ℓ → ∞.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Security against malicious operations</head><p>In the previous subsection, we showed that the protocol in Section III-B has the perfect security when the user and the servers follow the protocol. In this subsection, we prove that the protocol in Section III-B also guarantees the server and user secrecies even if the servers or the user apply malicious operations. Namely, we consider two malicious models: the malicious server model and the malicious user model.</p><p>The malicious server model considers the case that the servers apply malicious operations to obtain the target file index K but the user follows the protocol, i.e., the query generation and the recovery by the user are the same as the protocol in Section III-B. Our protocol is secure against this model since each of Q 1 and Q 2 is individually independent of the index K and the servers obtain no more information from the user except for Q 1 and Q 2 . Therefore the servers cannot obtain any information of K by malicious operations.</p><p>The second security model is the malicious user model, where the user sends malicious queries to the servers to obtain the non-targeted file information in addition to the target file W K . That is, the user sends malicious queries Q = (Q 1 , Q 2 ) to retrieve both of the file W K and some information of</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">W K c = (W 1 , . . . , W K-1 , W K+1 , . . . , W f ).</formula><p>Similarly to the malicious server model, we assume that the servers do not deviate from the protocol. Our protocol is also secure against this model since the user downloads the m ℓdimensional quantum system and the user is assumed to obtain W K ∈ {0, . . . , m ℓ -1}. That is, the user cannot obtain more information than W K . This security is precisely proved by the following relation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">I(A; W K c |W K , K, Q) ρW,Q = 0,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">A = A 1 ⊗ A 2 and I(•; •|•) ρ is the quantum conditional mutual information defined in Appendix B.</formula><p>Proof of Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. Since the user obtains the file W K , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">H(W K | A, K, Q) ρW,Q = 0,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where H(•|•) ρ is the quantum conditional entropy defined in Appendix B. Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_46">20</ref>) is equivalent to</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">H(A, W K |K, Q) ρW,Q = H(A |K, Q) ρW,Q .<label>(21)</label></formula><p>The relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> implies the following relations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">0 ≤ H(A |W K , K, Q) ρW,Q<label>(22)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_49">= H(A, W K |K, Q) ρW,Q -H(W K |K, Q) (23) = H(A |K, Q) ρW,Q -log m ℓ ≤ 0. (<label>24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_50">)</formula><p>The equality in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> follows from the condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, the independence between W K and (K, Q), and the uniform distribution of W K . The last inequality in <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref> follows from dim A = log m ℓ . Therefore, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">H(A |W K , K, Q) ρW,Q = 0<label>(25)</label></formula><p>which implies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. CONVERSE</head><p>In this section, we prove the converse bound</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">C α,∞,∞,∞ asymp ≤ 1<label>(26)</label></formula><p>for any α ∈ [0, 1). By replacing the notation of ρ W,Q defined in (1), let ρ w,z be the quantum state on the composite system n t=1 A t , where w is the file to be retrieved and z := (w c , q) for the collection w c of other m -1 files and the collection q of queries.</p><p>Applying <ref type="bibr">[31, (4.66)</ref>] to the choice σ z = (1/m) m-1 w=0 ρ w,z , for any s ∈ (0, 1), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">(1 -P err,z (Ψ (m) QPIR )) 1+s m s ≤ 1 m m-1 w=0 Tr ρ 1+s w,z σ -s z ,<label>(27)</label></formula><p>where P err,z (Ψ (m) QPIR ) is the error probability when z is fixed. For the completeness of the proof, we give the derivation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref> in Appendix C. Furthermore, we can bound the RHS of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_53">27</ref>) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">1 m m-1 w=0 Tr ρ 1+s w,z σ -s z ≤ 1 m m-1 w=0 Tr ρ w,z σ -s z = Tr σ 1-s z ≤ max σ Tr σ 1-s = max p d i=1 p 1-s i (a) = n t=1 dim A t s<label>(28)</label></formula><p>for d = n t=1 dim A t . Here, since x → x 1-s is concave, the maximum max p d i=1 p 1-s i is realized by the uniform distribution, which shows the equation (a). Combining ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_53">27</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_54">28</ref>), the error probability is upper bounded as</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">1 -P err (Ψ (m) QPIR ) = 1 -E Z P err,Z (Ψ (m) QPIR )<label>(29)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_56">≤ n t=1 dim A t m s 1+s . (<label>30</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p>For any sequence of QPIR protocols {Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">(m ℓ ) QPIR } ∞ ℓ=1 , if Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR satisfies R(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) = log m ℓ log n t=1 dim A t ≥ 1<label>(31)</label></formula><p>for any sufficiently large ℓ, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">n t=1 dim A t m ℓ → 0.</formula><p>Hence, by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_56">30</ref>), 1 -P err (Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) approaches zero, which implies <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CAPACITY OF MULTI-ROUND QPIR</head><p>In this section, we prove that the multi-round QPIR capacity is 1. First, as a generalization of the protocol description in Section II-A, we formally define the multi-round QPIR. Then, we propose the capacity theorem and the proof of the weak converse bound. Since the protocol in Section III-B has the QPIR rate 1, this protocol also achieves the multi-round QPIR capacity. The result in this section includes the result in the previous sections as the one-round QPIR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Formal Definition of Multi-Round QPIR Protocol</head><p>For any positive integer r, we give the formal description of the r-round QPIR protocol Ψ (m,r) QPIR . The information flow of the quantum systems is depicted in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. When r = 1, the protocol description is equivalent to the protocol defined in Section II-A.</p><p>Let n, f, m be integers greater than 1. Each of the servers serv 1 , . . . , serv n contains the whole copy of the uniformly and independently distributed f files W = (W 1 , . . . , W f ) ∈ {0, . . . , m -1} f . The t-th server serv t possesses a quantum system B t as local quantum register and the n servers share an entangled state ρ prev on the quantum system</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">B := B 1 ⊗ • • • ⊗ B n .</formula><p>The user chooses the target file index K ∈ {1, . . . , f} uniformly and independently of the files W 1 , . . . , W f . The user prepares the query</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">Q 1 = (Q 1 1 , Q 1 2 , . . . , Q 1 n ) depending on K.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enc</head><p>(1),Q [1] ,W serv</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">ρ prev W K User Servers Enc (2)</formula><p>,Q [2] ,W serv</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">Dec (1),K,Q [1] Dec (2),K,Q [2] B, W Q 1 C, K, Q [1] B, W, Q [1] A 1 A 2 Q 2 C, K, Q [2]</formula><p>B, W, Q [2]   W K Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The information flow in 2-round QPIR protocol. The servers have all files W = (W 1 , . . . , W f ) and the user retrieves the K-th file W K .</p><p>The user has a local quantum register C where the state is initialized depending on K and Q 1 . For i ∈ {1, . . . , r}, the i-th round is described as follows. Let Q i t be the query to serv t at round i, and we denote</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">Q i := (Q i 1 , . . . , Q i n ) and Q [i] t := (Q 1 t , . . . , Q i t )</formula><p>. The query Q i for round i is determined at round i -1. The user sends Q i t to the t-th server serv t . Depending on Q</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">[i]</formula><p>t and W , each server serv t applies a CPTP map</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">Enc (i),Q [i] t ,W servt from B t to A i t ⊗B t .</formula><p>That is, when the collection of the encoders is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">Enc (i),Q [i] ,W serv := n t=1 Enc (i),Q [i] t ,W servt , the state ρ B</formula><p>W on B is encoded as</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">ρ A i B W := Enc (i),Q [i] ,W serv (ρ B W ), where A i := A i 1 ⊗ • • • ⊗ A i n .</formula><p>Each server transmits the system A i t to the user and the received state of the user is the reduced state</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">ρ A i W := Tr B ρ A i B W .<label>(32)</label></formula><p>If i &lt; r, the user applies a quantum instrument</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">Dec (i),K,Q [i] = {Y i Q i+1 } Q i+1 ∈Q i+1 from A i ⊗ C to C depending on K and Q [i] := (Q 1 , . . . , Q i ), where Q i+1 1 × • • • × Q i+1 n</formula><p>is the set of queries at round i + 1 and Q i+1 is the measurement outcome. Then round i ends and round i + 1 starts. If i = r, i.e., at the final round, the user applies a POVM Dec (r),K,Q [r] = {Y M } m M=0 on A r ⊗C depending on K and Q [r] and outputs the measurement outcome M ∈ {0, . . . , m}. If M = m, it is considered as the retrieval failure.</p><p>Similarly to Section II-A, the security of the protocol is evaluated by the the error probability, the server secrecy, and the user secrecy defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">P err (Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := Pr W,K,Q 1 [M = W K ], S serv (Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := I(W K c ; user(Ψ (m,r) QPIR )|K), S user (Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := max t∈{1,...,n} I(K; serv t (Ψ (m,r) QPIR )).</formula><p>Given the QPIR protocol Ψ (m,r) QPIR , we define the upload cost, the download cost, and the QPIR rate by</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">U (Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := r i=1 log |Q i |,<label>(33)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_73">D(Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := r i=1 log dim A i ,<label>(34)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_74">R(Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) := log m D(Ψ (m,r) QPIR ) .<label>(35)</label></formula><p>Now, we define the r-round QPIR capacities with four parameters as follows. For an error constraint α ∈ [0, 1), server secrecy constraint β ∈ [0, ∞], user secrecy constraint γ ∈ [0, ∞], and upload constraint θ ∈ [0, ∞], the asymptotic security-constrained r-round capacity and the exact securityconstrained r-round capacity are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">C α,β,γ,θ asymp := sup (36) lim inf ℓ→∞ R(Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ), C α,β,γ,θ exact := sup (37) lim inf ℓ→∞ R(Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ),</formula><p>where the supremum is taken for sequences {m ℓ } ∞ ℓ=1 such that lim ℓ→∞ m ℓ = ∞ and for sequences {Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">(m ℓ ,r) QPIR } ∞</formula><p>ℓ=1 of r-round QPIR protocols to satisfy either <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> given by lim sup</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">ℓ→∞ P err (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ α, lim sup ℓ→∞ S serv (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ β, lim sup ℓ→∞ S user (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ γ, lim sup ℓ→∞ U (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) D(Ψ (m ℓ ) QPIR ) ≤ θ,<label>(36)</label></formula><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_78">P err (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ α, S serv (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ β, S user (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ γ, lim sup ℓ→∞ U (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) D(Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) ≤ θ. (<label>37</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_79">)</formula><p>The multi-round QPIR capacity is derived as follows.</p><p>Theorem V.1 (Multi-round QPIR capacity). Let r be any positive integer. When servers can share prior entanglement, the r-round QPIR capacity for f ≥ 2 files and n ≥ 2 servers is</p><formula xml:id="formula_80">C 0,β,γ,θ,r exact = C 0,β,γ,θ,r asymp = 1 (38) for any β, γ, θ ∈ [0, ∞].</formula><p>Proof. Eq. ( <ref type="formula">38</ref>) is proved by the following inequalities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_81">1 ≤ C 0,0,0,0,r exact ≤ C 0,β,γ,θ,r exact ≤ C 0,β,γ,θ,r asymp ≤ C 0,∞,∞,∞,r asymp ≤ 1.</formula><p>The first inequality holds by applying the rate-one QPIR protocol in Section III-B repetitively r times. The second, third, and fourth inequalities follow from the definition of the capacities. The last inequality is proved in Section V-B. Therefore, we obtain the theorem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Weak converse bound of multi-round QPIR capacity</head><p>We prove the converse bound</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">C 0,∞,∞,∞,r asymp ≤ 1. (<label>39</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">)</formula><p>Our proof comes from the fact that the multi-round QPIR protocol can be considered as a case of the Classical-Quantum (CQ) channel coding with classical feedback <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. In the CQ channel coding with classical feedback, the sender encodes a classical message W as a quantum state and sends the state over a fixed channel N . The receiver performs a decoding measurement on the received state and returns the measurement outcome to the sender. The sender and the receiver iterate this process r times while using the previous measurement outcomes for encoding and decoding. At the end of the protocol, the receiver receives the classical message W . The paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> proved that the capacity of this problem when the sender and the receiver have their local quantum registers, respectively. More specifically, the paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> also considered the energy constraint E that for a given Hamiltonian H on the input system of N , the input states ρ 1 , . . . , ρ r to N should satisfy r i=1 Tr ρ i H ≤ E. The CQ channel capacity is characterized by the following proposition. Proposition V.1 ( [32, <ref type="bibr">Theorem 4]</ref>). Let N be a quantum channel, r be the number of communication rounds, m be the size of the message set, H be the Hamiltonian on the input system of N , E be the energy constraint, and ε be the error probability. Suppose the sender and the receiver have local quantum registers, respectively. Then, for the CQ channel coding with classical feedback and energy constraint, we have the following inequality:</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">(1 -ε) log m ≤ sup ρ:Tr ρH≤E rH(N (ρ)) + h 2 (ε).<label>(40)</label></formula><p>The multi-round QPIR protocol can be considered as a case of this problem where the channel N is the identity channel and there is no energy constraint. To see this fact, we consider the the collection of the servers as the sender and the user as the receiver of the CQ channel coding, and focus on the communication of a classical message from the collection of the servers to the user. The servers sends to the user the systems A i over the identity channel and the user sends queries Q i to the servers as the measurement outcome on A i . The servers and the user have B and C as local quantum registers, respectively. At the end of the protocol, the user obtains the classical target file W K . Therefore, we can consider the multiround QPIR protocol as a CQ channel coding with classical feedback.</p><p>By the similar proof of [32, Theorem 4], we have the following proposition. Proposition V.2. Consider the CQ channel coding of a classical message W ∈ {0, . . . , m -1} from the sender to the receiver by sending quantum systems A 1 , . . . , A r sequentially over the identity channel and assisted by classical feedback. We assume that the sender and the receiver have local quantum registers, respectively. Let ρ A i W be the state on A i . For the uniformly chosen message W and the decoding output M , we define the error probability ε := Pr[M = W ]. Then we have the following inequality</p><formula xml:id="formula_85">(1 -ε) log m ≤ r i=1 H(ρ A i W ) + h 2 (ε) (41) ≤ r i=1 log dim A i +h 2 (ε),<label>(42)</label></formula><p>where h 2 (•) is the binary entropy function.</p><p>For the completeness of our paper, we give a proof of Proposition V.2 in Appendix D.</p><p>Remark V.1. Proposition V.2 is slightly different from <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4]</ref>. First, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4</ref>] considers an energy constraint on the quantum channel, Proposition V.2 assumes no energy constraint. Second, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4]</ref> considers the repetitive uses of a fixed quantum channel N , Proposition V.2 considers each use of the identity quantum channels over A 1 , . . . , A r . Even with these differences, we can apply the same proof steps of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4]</ref> and the first inequality of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. (35)</ref>] is the inequality (41). Now we prove the weak converse bound. We choose an arbitrary sequence {Ψ</p><formula xml:id="formula_86">(m ℓ ,r) QPIR } ∞ ℓ=1 of r-round QPIR protocols to satisfy ε ℓ := P err (Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) → 0 as ℓ → ∞.</formula><p>Considering the collection of the n servers as the sender and the user as the receiver of Proposition V.2, we can apply Proposition V.2 to the r-round QPIR protocol Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR with the classical message W K ∈ {0, . . . , m ℓ -1}, the transmitted quantum systems A 1 , . . . , A r , and the classical feedbacks Q 1 , . . . , Q r . In this case, ε and m of Proposition V.2 is substituted by ε ℓ and m ℓ , i.e., Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_85">42</ref>) is written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_87">(1 -ε ℓ ) log m ℓ ≤ r i=1 log dim A i +h 2 (ε ℓ ).<label>(43)</label></formula><p>Therefore, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_88">lim ℓ→∞ R(Ψ (m ℓ ,r) QPIR ) = lim ℓ→∞ log m ℓ r i=1 log dim A i ≤ 1,<label>(44)</label></formula><p>which implies (39).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>We have studied the capacity of QPIR with multiple servers when the servers share prior entanglement. Considering the user secrecy and the server secrecy, we defined two kinds of QPIR capacities: asymptotic and exact security-constrained capacities with upload constraint. We proved that both QPIR capacities are 1 for any security constraints and any upload constraint. We have constructed a capacity-achieving rateone protocol only with two servers when the file size is the square of an arbitrary integer. The converse has been proved by focusing on the download step of QPIR protocols. Furthermore, we have proved that the capacity of multi-round QPIR is also 1 by the weak converse bound.</p><p>It is an interesting open question whether the QPIR without shared entanglement also has an advantage over the classical PIR counterparts. This paper has considered the QPIR under the assumption of the prior entanglement and the quantum capacity of this case is strictly greater than the classical PIR capacity. The QPIR capacity without shared entanglement lies between the QPIR capacity of this paper and the classical PIR capacity. Therefore, it should be studied whether the quantum PIR capacity is strictly higher than the classical PIR capacity even without shared entanglement.</p><p>In this paper, we have assumed that the maximally entangled state can be shared by several servers. That is, we have made no restriction for shared entanglement. This setting is similar to the original studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> for the entangled assisted classical capacity for a noisy quantum channel because they have no restriction for shared entanglement. The recent paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> derived the entanglement-assisted classical capacity for a noisy quantum channel when shared entanglement is limited. For the extension, the study <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> invented several new methods, which are essential for this restriction. Therefore, it is remained as a future problem to extend our result to the case when the shared entangled state is restricted.</p><p>As another problem, we can consider the QPIR capacity when the channel from servers to user are noisy quantum channels. It is natural to apply quantum error corrections to each noisy quantum channels and apply our QPIR protocol over the virtually implemented noiseless channels by error correction. In this case, the transmission rate is given by the quantum capacity of the noisy quantum channel. For the converse part, we can easily extend the discussion of Section IV. In this extension, the obtained upper bound of the transmission rate is the classical capacity of the noisy quantum channel. Hence, this simple method does not yield the QPIR capacity with noisy quantum channels. Therefore, it is another challenging problem to calculate the QPIR capacity with noisy quantum channels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A PRELIMINARIES ON QUANTUM INFORMATION THEORY</head><p>In this section, we briefly introduce the fundamental framework of quantum information theory. For more detail, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>.</p><p>In classical information theory, the information is defined by an element x of a finite set X , and the information x is changed by a function f : X → Y, where Y is a finite set. Similarly, in quantum information theory, the quantum information is defined by a quantum state ρ on a quantum system A, and the quantum states ρ on A is modified by quantum operations κ from the states on A to the states on a quantum system B. Another difference between the two information theories is the measurement of information. If there is no error on the measuring apparatus, the measurement of classical information x is deterministic and does not change the information, i.e., measurement outcome is x and the information x is not changed after the measurement. However, the measurement of a quantum state outputs its outcome probabilistically and changes the state. In the following, we define the quantum system, quantum state, quantum operation, and quantum measurement.</p><p>A quantum system is defined by a finite-dimensional Hilbert space A. A vector x in A is denoted by |x , and x⊤ is denoted by x|. A quantum state is defined by a density matrix which is a positive semidefinite matrix ρ on A such that Tr ρ = 1. We denote the set of density matrices on A by S(A). When a state ρ is rank-one, i.e., ρ = |ψ ψ| for some unit vector |ψ , the state is called a pure state and is identified with the vector |ψ ∈ A. If a state ρ is not a pure state, it is called a mixed state. The composite system of A and B is defined by A ⊗ B. For any quantum state ρ ∈ S(A ⊗ B), the reduced state on A is described by Tr B ρ, where Tr B is the partial trace on the system B. A state ρ ∈ S(A ⊗ B) is called a separable state if ρ is written as ρ = i p i σ i ⊗ τ i for states σ i ∈ S(A), τ i ∈ S(B), and a probability distribution {p i } i . A state ρ ∈ S(A ⊗ B) is called an entangled state if ρ is not separable.</p><p>A quantum operation is defined by a Completely Positive Trace-Preserving (CPTP) linear map from S(A) to S(B). A linear map κ is called a positive map if κ maps a positive semidefinite matrix to a positive semidefinite matrix, and is called a Completely-Positive (CP) map if the linear map κ⊗ι C n is a positive map for any positive integer n, where ι C n is the identity map on S(C n ). An example of quantum operations is κ U (ρ) := UρU † for a unitary matrix U on A. By the operation κ U , a pure state |ψ ∈ A is mapped to the pure state U|ψ ∈ A.</p><p>A quantum measurement is defined by an instrument. A set {κ ω } ω∈Ω of CP maps from S(A) to S(B) is called an instrument if for any quantum state ρ ∈ S(A), ω∈Ω Tr κ ω (ρ) = 1.</p><p>With probability Tr κ ω (ρ), the measurement outcome is ω and the state after the measurement is κ ω (ρ)/Tr κ ω (ρ). When one is interested only in the measurement probability and the outcome, the measurement is described by a Positive Operator-Valued Measure (POVM). A set {M ω } ω∈Ω of positive semidefinite matrices is called an POVM if ω∈Ω M ω = I. With probability Tr ρM ω , the measurement outcome is ω.</p><p>Any quantum state ρ is diagonalized as ρ = i p i |i i| for a probability distribution {p i } i . For a state ρ = i p i |i i|, von Neumann entropy is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_89">H(ρ) := H({p i }),<label>(45)</label></formula><p>where H(•) in the right-hand side of (45) is Shannon entropy H({p i }) :=i p i log p i . For any state ρ ∈ S(A ⊗ B), we use the notation</p><formula xml:id="formula_90">H(A) ρ := H(Tr B ρ), H(B) ρ := H(Tr A ρ), H(A, B) ρ := H(ρ).</formula><p>For any state ρ ∈ S(A⊗B⊗C), the quantum conditional entropy, quantum mutual information, and quantum conditional mutual information are defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_91">H(A|B) ρ := H(A, B) ρ -H(B) ρ ,<label>(46)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_92">I(A; B) ρ := H(A) ρ + H(B) ρ -H(A, B) ρ ,<label>(47)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_93">I(A; B|C) ρ := I(A; B, C) ρ -I(A; C) ρ .<label>(48)</label></formula><p>When a quantum state ρ X ∈ S(A) is prepared depending on the random variable X ∈ X , the state on the composite system of A and X is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_94">ρ = x∈X Pr[X = x] • ρ x ⊗ |x x|.</formula><p>For convenience, we denote H(•) ρX := H(•) ρ and I(•) ρX := I(•) ρ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX C DERIVATION OF (27)</head><p>For the derivation of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_53">27</ref>), we use the data-processing inequality of quantum relative Rényi entropy. When s ∈ (0, 1), quantum relative Rényi entropy is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_95">D 1+s (ρ σ) := 1 s Tr ρ 1+s σ -s<label>(49)</label></formula><p>for any states ρ and σ such that supp(ρ) ⊂ supp(σ), and D 1+s satisfies the data-processing inequality with respect to measurements:</p><formula xml:id="formula_96">D 1+s (ρ σ) ≥ D 1+s (P M ρ P M σ ),<label>(50)</label></formula><p>where P M ρ and P M ρ are probability distributions after the measurement M = {M i } i on ρ and σ, respectively, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_97">P M ρ = i (Tr ρM i ) • |i i|, P M σ = i (Tr σM i ) • |i i|.</formula><p>Next, we prepare the following notations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_98">σ z := 1 m m-1 w=0 ρ w,z , ρz := 1 m m-1 w=0 |w w| ⊗ ρ w,z , σz := 1 m m-1 w=0 |w w| ⊗ σ z , Ỹ := m-1 w=0 |w w| ⊗ Y w , M = { Ỹ, I -Ỹ},</formula><p>where {Y w } m w=0 is the decoding measurement defined in Section II. With these notations, we have where (a) is from (51) and ( <ref type="formula">52</ref>) and (b) is from (50).</p><formula xml:id="formula_99">Tr ρz Ỹ = 1 m m-1 w=0 Tr ρ w,z Y w = 1 -P err,z (Ψ (m) QPIR ),<label>(51)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX D PROOF OF PROPOSITION V.2</head><p>For the proof of Proposition V.2, we follow the proof of <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr">Theorem 4]</ref>. Before the proof, we prepare two lemmas from <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. </p><p>For the proof, we formally describe the communication protocol as follows. We denote the local registers of the sender and the receiver before the communication by B 0 and C 0 . Let A 0 = C. At round i ∈ {1, . . . , r}, the receiver applies a quantum instrument from A i-1 ⊗ C i-1 to C i depending on Q [i-1] and sends the measurement outcome Q i to the sender Then, the sender applies a quantum operation from B i-1 to A i ⊗ B i depending on W and Q [i] := (Q 1 , . . . , Q i ), and sends A i to the receiver. After the final rth-round, the sender applies a POVM on A r ⊗ C r depending on Q [r] and the measurement outcome M is the decoding output. Now, we prove Proposition V.2. First, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_101">(1 -ε) log m (a) ≤ I(W ; M ) + h 2 (ε) (58) (b) ≤ I(W ; A r C r Q [r] ) + h 2 (ε),<label>(59)</label></formula><p>where (a) is from Fano's inequality</p><formula xml:id="formula_102">H(W |M ) ≤ ε log m + h 2 (ε)<label>(60)</label></formula><p>and the uniform distribution of W , and (b) is from the dataprocessing inequality for the decoding POVM. Then, it is enough to derive the inequality</p><formula xml:id="formula_103">I(W ; A r C r Q [r] ) ≤ r i=1 H(ρ A i W )<label>(61)</label></formula><p>for the proof of Proposition V.2.</p><p>To derive (61), we apply Lemma D.1 and Lemma D.2 as follows. Note that there is no constraint in the size of local registers. Thus, without losing generality, we assume that the sender's and the receiver's local registers are sufficiently large that the joint state on the entire protocol is always written as pure states. Since the operations at each round can be considered as a one-way LOCC map, we can apply Lemma D.1 for (W, F, A, B, A ′ , B ′ , X) := (W,</p><formula xml:id="formula_104">Q [i-1] , B i-1 , A i-1 ⊗C i-1 , A i ⊗ B i , C i , Q i ): I(W ; C i Q [i] ) + H(C i |W Q [i] ) ≤ I(W ; A i-1 C i-1 Q [i-1] ) + H(A i-1 C i-1 |W Q [i-1] ).</formula><p>Furthermore, applying Lemma D.2 with (W, F, A, B) := (W, Q [i] , A i , C i ). we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_105">I(W ; A i C i Q [i] ) + H(A i C i |W Q [i] ) ≤ H(A i ) + I(W ; C i Q [i] ) + H(C i |W Q [i] ).<label>(62)</label></formula><p>Combining the above two inequalities, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_106">I(W ; A i C i Q [i] ) + H(A i C i |W Q [i] ) ≤ H(A i ) + I(W ; A i-1 C i-1 Q [i-1] ) + H(A i-1 C i-1 |W Q [i-1] )<label>(63)</label></formula><p>Applying the inequality (63) recursively, we obtain the desired inequality (61) as </p><formula xml:id="formula_107">I(W ; A r C r Q [r] ) ≤ I(W ; A r C r Q [r] ) + H(A r C r |W Q [r] ) (c) ≤ r i=2 H(A i ) + I(W ; A 1 C 1 Q 1 ) + H(A 1 C 1 |W Q 1 ) (d) ≤ r i=1 H(A i ) + I(W ; C 1 Q 1 ) + H(C 1 |W Q 1 )<label>(e)</label></formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>+ ( 1 -w=0</head><label>1</label><figDesc>), (51), and (52), we can derive Eq. (27) similarly as[31, (4.66)]:(1 -P err,z (Ψ (m) QPIR )) 1+s m s (a) ≤ (Tr ρz Ỹ) 1+s (Tr σz Ỹ) -s ≤ (Tr ρz Ỹ) 1+s (Tr σz Ỹ) -s Tr ρz Ỹ) 1+s (1 -Tr σz Ỹ) -s = exp sD 1+s (P M ρz P M σz )(b)≤ exp(sD 1+s (ρ z σz ))Tr ρ 1+s w,z σ -s z ,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Lemma D. 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>[32,  Lemma 2]). Let τ W F AB be a classicalquantum state such thatτ W F AB = w,f p(w, f )|w, f w, f | ⊗ τ AB|wf , (53)where τ AB|wf are pure states. Let M be one-way Local Operations and Classical Communication (LOCC) map from A ⊗ B to A ′ ⊗ B ′ ⊗ X, where X is a classical system which is sent from B to A. Then, we haveI(W ; B ′ F X) + H(B ′ |W F X) (54) ≤ I(W ; BF ) + H(B|W F ).(55)Lemma D.2 ( [32, Lemma 3]). Let τ W F AB be a classicalquantum state defined in (53). Then I(W ; ABF ) + H(AB|W F ) (56) ≤ H(A) + I(W ; BF ) + H(B|W F ).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>= r i=1 H</head><label>i=1</label><figDesc>(A i ),where (c) is derived by applying (63) recursively for i = r, r -1, . . . , 2, (d) is from (62), and (e) is obtained as follows: I(W ; C 1 Q 1 ) = 0 because the receiver prepares the state of C 1 ⊗ Q 1 independently of the sender's message W , and H(C 1 |W Q 1 ) = 0 since the initial state of the local register C 1 is a pure state.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Mathematics, <rs type="funder">Nagoya University</rs>. He is also a <rs type="programName">Research Fellow of the Japan Society of the Promotion of Science (JSPS) from 2020. He awarded the School of Engineering Science Outstanding Student Award in 2017 and Graduate School</rs> of <rs type="person">Mathematics Award</rs> for Outstanding Masters Thesis in 2019. His research interests include classical and quantum information theory and its applications to secure communication protocols. <rs type="person">Masahito Hayashi</rs> (M'<rs type="grantNumber">06-SM'13-F'17</rs>) was born in Japan in 1971. He received the B.S. degree from the <rs type="funder">Faculty of Sciences in Kyoto University, Japan</rs>, in 1994 and the M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in Mathematics from <rs type="funder">Kyoto University, Japan</rs>, in 1996 and 1999, respectively. He worked in Kyoto University as a Research Fellow of the <rs type="institution">Japan Society of the Promotion of Science (JSPS)</rs> from <rs type="grantNumber">1998</rs> to 2000, and worked in the <rs type="institution">Laboratory for Mathematical Neuroscience, Brain Science Institute</rs>, RIKEN from 2000 to 2003, and worked in <rs type="institution">ERATO Quantum Computation and Information Project, Japan Science and Technology Agency (JST)</rs> as the Research Head from 2000 to 2006. He also worked in the Superrobust Computation Project <rs type="projectName">Information Science and Technology Strategic Core</rs> (21st Century COE by <rs type="funder">MEXT) Graduate School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo</rs> as Adjunct Associate Professor from 2004 to 2007. He worked in the <rs type="institution">Graduate School of Information Sciences, Tohoku University</rs> as Associate Professor from 2007 to 2012. In 2012, he joined the <rs type="institution">Graduate School of Mathematics, Nagoya University</rs> as <rs type="person">Professor. Also</rs>, he was appointed in <rs type="affiliation">Centre for Quantum Technologies, National University of Singapore</rs> as Visiting Research Associate Professor from 2009 to 2012 and as Visiting Research Professor from 2012 to now. He worked in Center for Advanced Intelligence Project, RIKEN as a Visiting Scientist from 2017 to 2020. He worked in <rs type="institution">Shenzhen Institute for Quantum Science and Engineering, Southern University of Science and Technology, Shenzhen, China</rs> as a Visiting Professor from 2018 to 2020, and in <rs type="institution">Center for Quantum Computing, Peng Cheng Laboratory, Shenzhen, China</rs> as a Visiting Professor from 2019 to 2020. In 2020, he joined <rs type="funder">Shenzhen Institute for Quantum Science and Engineering, Southern University of Science and Technology, Shenzhen, China as Chief Research Scientist</rs>. In 2011, he received <rs type="grantName">Information Theory Society Paper Award</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">2011</rs>) for "<rs type="projectName">Information-Spectrum Approach to Second-Order Coding Rate in Channel Coding</rs>". In 2016, he received the <rs type="funder">Japan Academy</rs> Medal from the Japan Academy and the <rs type="funder">JSPS Prize from Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</rs>. In 2006, he published the book "<rs type="projectName">Quantum Information: An Introduction</rs>" from Springer, whose revised version was published as "<rs type="projectName">Quantum Information Theory: Mathematical Foundation</rs>" from Graduate Texts in Physics, Springer in 2016. In 2016, he published other two books "<rs type="programName">Group Representation for Quantum Theory</rs>" and "<rs type="projectName">A Group Theoretic Approach to Quantum Information" from Springer. He is on the Editorial Board of International Journal of Quantum Information and International Journal On Advances in Security</rs>. His research interests include classical and quantum information theory and classical and quantum statistical inference.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>SS is supported by</head><p><rs type="grantName">Rotary Yoneyama Memorial Master Course Scholarship</rs> (YM), <rs type="funder">Lotte Foundation Scholarship</rs>, and <rs type="funder">JSPS</rs> <rs type="grantName">Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows</rs> No. <rs type="grantNumber">JP20J11484</rs>. MH is supported in part by <rs type="funder">Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory</rs> (Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">2019B121203002</rs>), a <rs type="grantName">JSPS Grant-in-Aids for Scientific Research</rs> (A) No.<rs type="grantNumber">17H01280</rs> and for Scientific Research (B) No.<rs type="grantNumber">16KT0017</rs>, and <rs type="funder">Kayamori Foundation of Information Science Advancement</rs>.</p><p><rs type="institution">TABLE I CAPACITIES OF CLASSICAL AND QUANTUM PIRS Classical PIR Capacity Quantum PIR Capacity</rs> PIR</p><p>* n, f: the numbers of servers and files, respectively. † Shared randomness among servers is necessary. ‡ Capacities are derived with the strong converse bounds. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> This paper Paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> Server secrecy Yes No Capacity 1 (1-n -1 )/(1-n -f )</p></div>
<div><head>TABLE II COMPARISON OF PROTOCOLS IN THIS PAPER AND</head></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_vBuVgUx">
					<idno type="grant-number">06-SM&apos;13-F&apos;17</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Research Fellow of the Japan Society of the Promotion of Science (JSPS) from 2020. He awarded the School of Engineering Science Outstanding Student Award in 2017 and Graduate School</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_cx3QChu">
					<idno type="grant-number">1998</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Information Science and Technology Strategic Core</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_3uGkkwr">
					<idno type="grant-number">2011</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Information Theory Society Paper Award</orgName>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Information-Spectrum Approach to Second-Order Coding Rate in Channel Coding</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_B5KZyfK">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Quantum Information: An Introduction</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_ZCZ4QuY">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Quantum Information Theory: Mathematical Foundation</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Group Representation for Quantum Theory</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_wBr9HHy">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">A Group Theoretic Approach to Quantum Information&quot; from Springer. He is on the Editorial Board of International Journal of Quantum Information and International Journal On Advances in Security</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_q3dSbyW">
					<orgName type="grant-name">Rotary Yoneyama Memorial Master Course Scholarship</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_rkfbd38">
					<idno type="grant-number">JP20J11484</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_VAX5qs5">
					<idno type="grant-number">2019B121203002</idno>
					<orgName type="grant-name">JSPS Grant-in-Aids for Scientific Research</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_kHrn5xF">
					<idno type="grant-number">17H01280</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_N69aqpm">
					<idno type="grant-number">16KT0017</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTUM INFORMATION MEASURES</head><p>In this section, we introduce quantum information measures necessary for the analysis of QPIR protocols.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Private information retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kushilevitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Earlier version in FOCS&apos;95</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="965" to="981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computationally Private Information Retrieval with Polylogarithmic Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cachin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Micali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Cryptology -EUROCRYPT &apos;99</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="402" to="414" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First CPIR Protocol with Data-Dependent Computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lipmaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Information Security and Cryptology</title>
		<meeting>the 12th International Conference on Information Security and Cryptology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="210" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust information-theoretic private information retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beimel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Security in Communication Networks (SCN&apos;02)</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd International Conference on Security in Communication Networks (SCN&apos;02)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="341" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimally Robust Private Information Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Devet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Heninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">21st USENIX Security Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-08">August 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exponential lower bound for 2-query locally decodable codes via a quantum argument</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kerenidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 35th ACM STOC</title>
		<meeting>35th ACM STOC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum symmetrically-private information retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kerenidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Processing Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secure quantum private information retrieval using phaseencoded queries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Olejnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22313</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum Private Information Retrieval with Sublinear Communication Complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Gall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theory of Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information cost of quantum communication protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kerenidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Laurière</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Le</forename><surname>Gall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rennela</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Quantum information &amp; computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="196" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum Private Information Retrieval has linear communication complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ä</forename><surname>Baumeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Broadbent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cryptology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Quantum Advantage in Information Theoretic Single-Server PIR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aharonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Brakerski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-M</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sattath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Cryptology -EUROCRYPT 2019</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ishai</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rijmen</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cham</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Capacity of Private Information Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jafar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity-Achieving Private Information Retrieval Codes with Optimal Message Size and Upload Cost</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7613" to="7627" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Capacity of Symmetric Private Information Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jafar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2016 IEEE Globecom Workshops (GC Wkshps)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Private Information Retrieval for Coded Storage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)</title>
		<meeting>IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2842" to="2846" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Private information retrieval from coded databases with colluding servers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Freij-Hollanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Gnilke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hollanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Karpuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Appl. Algebra Geometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Capacity of Private Information Retrieval from Coded Databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Banawan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ulukus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving maximum distance separable private information retrieval capacity with linear codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rosnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Graell I Amat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4243" to="4273" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An MDS-PIR capacity-achieving protocol for distributed storage using non-MDS linear codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rosnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Graell I Amat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Symp. Inf. Theory</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Symp. Inf. Theory<address><addrLine>Vail, CO, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">Jun. 17-22, 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Capacity of Private Information Retrieval from Coded, Colluding, and Adversarial Servers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Holzbaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Freij-Hollanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hollanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Information Theory Workshop</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Information Theory Workshop</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiround Private Information Retrieval: Capacity and Storage Overhead</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jafar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5743" to="5754" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How to exchange secrets with oblivious transfer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR-81</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Harvard University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A randomized protocol for signing contracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Even</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Goldreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lempel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="647" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Founding crytpography on oblivious transfer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kilian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 1988 ACM Annual Symposium on Theory of Computing</title>
		<meeting>1988 ACM Annual Symposium on Theory of Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Founding Cryptography on Oblivious Transfer -Efficiently</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ishai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Prabhakaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sahai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="591" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CRYPTO</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protecting data privacy in private information retrieval schemes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gertner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ishai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kushilevitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Malkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC 98</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="592" to="629" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum multi-prover interactive proof systems with limited prior entanglement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Matsumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer and System Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consequences and limits of nonlocal strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cleve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Toner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Watrous</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 19th IEEE Annual Conference on Computational Complexity</title>
		<meeting>19th IEEE Annual Conference on Computational Complexity</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="249" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A classical leash for a quantum system: command of quantum systems via rigidity of CHSH games</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Reichardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Unger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Vazirani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 4th conference on Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS &apos;13)</title>
		<meeting>the 4th conference on Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS &apos;13)<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Quantum Information Theory: Mathematical Foundation</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>An Introduction Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Graduate Texts in Physics Second edition of Quantum Information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entropy Bound for the Classical Capacity of a Quantum Channel Assisted by Classical Feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Quek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wilde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2019 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory</title>
		<meeting>the 2019 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory<address><addrLine>Paris, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="254" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum Information Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wilde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tomamichel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Quantum Information Processing with Finite Resources: Mathematical Foundations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SpringerBriefs in Mathematical Physics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement-assisted classical capacity of noisy quantum channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Smolin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3081</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entanglement-assisted capacity of a quantum channel and the reverse shannon theorem</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2637" to="2655" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Permutation Enhances Classical Communication Assisted by Entangled States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 2020 IEEE Int. Symp. Information Theory (ISIT 2020)</title>
		<meeting>2020 IEEE Int. Symp. Information Theory (ISIT 2020)<address><addrLine>Los Angeles, California, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capacity of Quantum Private Information Retrieval with Multiple Servers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2019 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)</title>
		<meeting>2019 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1727" to="1731" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Seunghoan Song (S&apos;20) received the B.E. degree from Osaka University in 2017 and the Master of Mathematical Science degree from Nagoya University in 2019. He is currently pursuing Ph</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>D. degree at the Graduate School of</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
