<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Classical and Quantum Resources in Perfect Teleportation</title>
				<funder ref="#_tuDmVDu">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundation of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_Tkq3c9v">
					<orgName type="full">National Natural Science Foundations of China</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_RJ6gaAb">
					<orgName type="full">Innovation Program for Quantum Science and Technology</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Nankai Zhide Foundations</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2025-07-24">July 24, 2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dian</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jing-Ling</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<email>chenjl@nankai.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fu-Lin</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>flzhang@tju.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Theoretical Physics Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Chern Institute of Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Nankai University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>300071</postCode>
									<settlement>Tianjin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tianjin University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>300072</postCode>
									<settlement>Tianjin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Classical and Quantum Resources in Perfect Teleportation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2025-07-24">July 24, 2025</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1DCF5A27717BCE8718C3BAA56C3C3280</idno>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2506.18577v2[quant-ph]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T12:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>teleportation</term>
					<term>entanglement</term>
					<term>classical information</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We propose a teleportation protocol that enables perfect transmission of a qubit using a partially entangled two-qutrit quantum channel. Within our scheme, we analyze the relationship among the three key ingredients of teleportation: (i) the quantum channel, (ii) the sender's (Alice's) measurement operations, and (iii) the classical information transmitted to the receiver (Bob). Compared to Gour's protocol [1], our scheme requires less entanglement of Alice's measurement and fewer classical bits sent to Bob. Our results also show a trade-off between these two resources and derive a lower bound for their sum, quantifying their interplay in the teleportation process.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Quantum teleportation is a protocol that enables the transmission of an unknown quantum state from a sender (Alice) to a receiver (Bob), utilizing a quantum channel and assisted by classical communication. This process, first proposed by Bennett et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, can be perfectly implemented by sharing a maximally entangled two-qubit Bell state between Alice and Bob. Alice performs a joint measurement on the quantum state to be transmitted and a subsystem of the pre-shared Bell state. She then sends the corresponding measurement results to Bob via classical communication. Finally, Bob applies specific unitary operations to his state, recovering the target state with 100% success probability.</p><p>A key feature of quantum teleportation lies in the nonuniqueness of its protocols. Significant extensions beyond the original scheme include: probabilistic teleportation with partially entangled pure states <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, teleportation in high dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and controlled teleportation involving third-party supervisors <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>. These protocol variants now play a pivotal role in various quantum communication scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Despite the diversity of protocols, they all share a common requirement: the consumption of quantum entanglement and classical communication resources. The former manifests in the entanglement of the quantum channel and the entanglement resources of the sender's joint measurement, while the latter depends on the amount of classical information that must be transmitted to reconstruct the quantum state. The interplay among these three key factors remains an open problem in quantum teleportation theory. Specifically, for a fixed quantum channel, what is the fundamental relationship between the measurement resource requirement and the classical communication cost? Can this relationship be quantitatively characterized?</p><p>We address these questions for the special case of faithfully transmitting a qubit using arbitrary partially entangled two-qutrit pure states. Through a perspective that interprets Alice's measurement basis as a unitary transformation of the computational basis, we extend the teleportation protocol from two-qubit to two-qutrit quantum channels. Our scheme employs five free parameters to characterize the measurement basis, offering broader applicability compared to existing protocols: Gour's protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> requires only two parameters but imposes a fixed classical cost log 2 d a (where d a represents the total dimension of Alice's system), regardless of channel entanglement. Chen et al's protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> further reduces the parameter count to one, though this comes at the expense of being restricted to partially entangled states with degenerate Schmidt coefficients. In contrast, our protocol combines these two characteristics: (i) entanglementdependent classical communication cost for resource optimization, (ii) compatibility with adaptability to arbitrary partially entangled two-qutrit channels.</p><p>Based on the Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>'s definition of the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement basis, we analyze the relationship among the above three key ingredients. The results show that our protocol achieves greater resource efficiency than prior approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref> in both classical communication costs and quantum entanglement consumption for any perfect-teleportation-enabled two-qutrit partially entangled pure state. Moreover, we derive the lower bound on the sum of these two resource costs under fixed channel conditions, revealing a constrained trade-off relationship between classical and quantum resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. TWO-QUBIT CHANNEL</head><p>To propose a two-qutrit channel protocol for qubit transmission, we reconstruct the standard teleportation scheme originally designed for two-qubit channels. First, we briefly revisit the conventional approach that utilizes two-qubit Bell states as the quantum channel. Following the standard protocol, the sender (Alice) and the recipient (Bob) pre-shared an EPR pair. When Alice needs to transmit an unknown qubit</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">|φ 1 = α|0 1 + β|1 1<label>(1)</label></formula><p>to Bob (satisfying the normalization condition |α|</p><p>2 + |β| 2 = 1), she first applies a controlled-Not gate (qubit 1 as the control and qubit 2 as the target) and follows a Hadamard gate (acting on qubit 1) to her local qubits. She then measures qubits 1 and 2 in the computational basis, obtaining a 2-bit outcome m ∈ {00, 01, 10, 11}. After obtaining the outcome, Bob applies the corresponding Pauli gate (1, X, Z or Y ) to qubit 3 to recover the state |φ 1 perfectly. Figure 1 illustrates the process of the standard quantum teleportation protocol, where |Φ 23 represents the pre-shared EPR pair, D † 12 denotes the unitary operation performed by Alice, and W M1M2 corresponds to the state recovery operation implemented by Bob based on the received classical information (M 1 , M 2 ).</p><p>Notice that the pre-shared EPR pair can be replaced by a two-qubit partially entangled pure state</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">|Φ 23 = a 0 |00 23 + a 1 |11 23<label>(2)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 j=0 |a j | 2 = 1</formula><p>, where perfect teleportation is attainable if and only if |Φ 23 is maximally entangled <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Our subsequent analysis will utilize such partially entangled states (and their high-dimensional extensions) as the quantum channel. Without loss of generality, one can assume that the Schmidt coefficients a j=0,1 are real numbers and 0 ≤ a 0 ≤ a 1 . Meanwhile, the unitary operation D † 12 and the following measurement of the computational basis can be regarded as a measurement of the Bell basis. This implies that constructing Alice's joint measurement basis reduces to designing the unitary operator D 12 . Since Bob's recovery operation depends on the elements of operator D 12 , the essential step of the teleportation protocol lies in the design of this unitary operator.</p><p>In our scheme, the unitary operator corresponding to Alice's joint measurement is of the form </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D 12 =     u 11 0 0 u 12 u 21 cosη v 22 e -iδ sinη v 21 sinη u 22 cosη 0 v 12 e -iδ v 11 0 -u 21 sinη v 22 e -iδ cosη v 21 cosη -u 22 sinη     (3)</formula><p>After Alice measured qubits 1 and 2 using the computational basis, Bob's qubit 3 collapsed into the form of |φ j± 3 = α|φ α 3 + β|φ β 3 . This process is equivalent to performing a joint measurement of qubits 1 and 2 in the orthonormal basis</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">|ψ j ± 12 = j ′ -1, j -1| 12 D 12 with j, j ′ = 1, 2.</formula><p>At this stage, our protocol contains multiple undetermined parameters due to the lack of certain prior conditions (for example, the values of Schmidt coefficients a j=0,1 ). We shall show that perfect teleportation in our scheme can only be achieved when the quantum channel is maximally entangled. For the protocol to succeed perfectly, the following conditions must hold: (i)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">φ α |φ α = φ β |φ β , (ii) φ α |φ β = φ β |φ α = 0,</formula><p>yielding four constraint equations in total. By leveraging the unitarity of matrices U and V , and the normalization condition</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1 j=0 a 2 j = 1, we have a 2 0 = u 2 12 = v 2 12 = u 2 21 = v 2 21 and a 2 1 = u 2 11 = v 2 11 = u 2 22 = v 2 22</formula><p>. Thus, the original four conditions simplify to the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">a 2 0 u 2 11 = a 2 1 u 2 12 , (a 2 0 u 2 21 +a 2 1 u 2 22</formula><p>•e iδ ) sin η cos η = 0, (5) where we have assumed u kl = v kl without loss of generality.</p><p>It is easy to show that the conditions hold if</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">a 2 0 u 2 21 + a 2 1 u 2 22 • e iδ = 0 or sin η cos η = 0. If a 2 0 u 2 21 + a 2 1 u 2 22</formula><p>• e iδ = 0, one can obtain that e iδ = -1, a 2 0 = a 2 1 = 1/2, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">|ψ 1+ 12 = 1 √ 2 (|00 + |11 ) 12 , |ψ 1-12 = 1 √ 2 (|10 -|01 ) 12 ,<label>(6a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">|ψ 2+ 12 = 1 √ 2 [cos η(-|00 +|11 )-sin η(|10 +|01 )] 12 , |ψ 2-12 = 1 √ 2 [-sin η(-|00 +|11 )-cos η(|10 +|01 )] 12 .<label>(6b)</label></formula><p>By performing a unitary transformation</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">U 1 = |0 1 (cos η 0| + sin η 1|) 1 + |1 1 (-sin η 0| + cos η 1|)</formula><p>1 , the maximally entangled states in Eq. (6b) can be transformed as Bell bases 1 √ 2 (|00 -|11 ) 12 and 1 √ 2 (|10 + |01 ) 12 . Thus, this new scheme is equivalent to the standard one. If sin η cos η = 0, one can obtain that a 2 0 u 2 12 = a 2 1 u 2 11 , then the same conclusion holds. III. TWO-QUTRIT CHANNEL</p><p>Extending the previous protocol to the two-qutrit channel follows naturally. Similarly to the case of the two-qubit channel, the state that Alice can expect to deliver is still in the form of Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">1</ref>).</p><p>The transmission channel is described by</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">|Φ 23 = a 0 |00 23 + a 1 |11 23 + a 2 |22 23 ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where the Schmidt coefficients a j=0,1,2 are real numbers satisfying 0 ≤ a j &lt; 1 and 2 j=0 a 2 j = 1. The total state in the teleportation takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">|Ψ 123 = |φ 1 |Φ 23 = [α(a 0 |000 + a 1 |011 + a 2 |022 ) + β(a 0 |100 + a 1 |111 + a 2 |122 )] 123 .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Compared with the two-qubit channel case, these basis vectors {|00 , |01 , |02 , |10 , |11 , |12 } admit a richer variety of possible decompositions into mutually orthogonal subspaces.</p><p>After imposing perfect teleportation constraints, there remain three types of identity-dimensional orthogonal subspace decompositions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">{|00 , |01 , |12 } and {|10 , |11 , |02 }, {|00 , |11 , |02 } and {|10 , |01 , |12 }, or {|10 , |01 , |02 } and {|00 , |11 , |12 }.</formula><p>The selection of subspaces for constructing the measurement bases is related to the size of the Schmidt coefficients. If the Schmidt coefficients satisfy max{a j } j=0,1,2 = a 1 , then Alice's measurements can be chosen by a unitary transformation acting on the subspace of {|00 , |11 , |02 } and {|10 , |01 , |12 }. The unitary operators read as</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">U =   u 11 u 12 u 13 u 21 u 22 u 23 u 31 u 32 u 33   , V =   v 11 v 12 •e iδ1 v 13 •e iδ2 v 21 v 22 •e iδ1 v 23 •e iδ2 v 31 v 32 •e iδ1 v 33 •e iδ2   ,</formula><p>where u kl , v kl , and δ m (k, l = 1, 2, 3, m = 1, 2) are real numbers. The constraint equations for the unitary matrix elements can be directly derived from conditions (i) and (ii) for perfect quantum teleportation. Note that the number of constraint equations is significantly fewer than the number of unknown parameters, making it particularly challenging to determine the explicit form of the measurement bases analytically. To simplify our analysis, we assume that u kl = v kl and U are restricted to be a rotation matrix R(θ 1 , θ 2 , θ 3 ) within the SO(3) group.</p><p>For a two-qutrit channel, the unitary operator corresponding to Alice's joint measurement is of the form </p><formula xml:id="formula_17">D 12 =       </formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">|φ 1+ 3 = α(a 0 u 11 |0 +a 2 u 13 |2 ) 3 +βa 1 u 12 |1 3 , |φ 1-3 = α(a 0 u 21 |0 +a 2 u 23 |2 ) 3 +βa 1 u 22 |1 3 , |φ 2+ 3 = β(a 0 u 11 |0 +a 2 u 13 •e -iδ2 |2 ) 3 +αa 1 u 12 •e -iδ1 |1 3 , |φ 2-3 = β(a 0 u 21 |0 +a 2 u 23 •e -iδ2 |2 ) 3 +αa 1 u 22 •e -iδ1 |1 3 , |φ 3± 3 = 1 √ 2 [α(±a 0 u 31 |0 +a 1 u 32 •e -iδ1 |1 ±a 2 u 33 |2 ) +β(a 0 u 31 |0 ±a 1 u 32 |1 +a 2 u 33 •e -iδ2 |2 )] 3 .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>The constraint equations for the unitary matrix elements and the Schmidt coefficients are given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">a 2 0 u 2 11 + a 2 2 u 2 13 = a 2 1 u 2 12 , a 2 0 u 2 21 + a 2 2 u 2 23 = a 2 1 u 2 22 ,<label>(11a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">a 2 0 u 2 31 + a 2 1 u 2 32 • e iδ1 + a 2 2 u 2 33 • e -iδ2 = 0. (<label>11b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">)</formula><p>Then the probabilities of Alice's outcome are given by the overlap P j± = 3 φ j± |φ j± 3 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">P 1+ = P 2+ = a 2 0 u 2 11 + a 2 2 u 2 13 , P 1-= P 2-= a 2 0 u 2 21 + a 2 2 u 2 23 , P 3± = 1 2 (a 2 0 u 2 31 + a 2 1 u 2 32 + a 2 2 u 2 23 ).<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Next, one can easily prove that our scheme is sufficient and necessary for all quantum channels satisfying the perfect teleportation condition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> When max{a j } j=0,1,2 = a 1 ≤ 1/ √ 2, Eqs. (11a) allow expressing two rotation angles (e.g., θ 1 and θ 2 ) in terms of the third (θ 3 ), while constraining its admissible range. This guarantees the existence of a solution for all valid channels. In this sense, our scheme is necessary for any quantum channel satisfying max{a j } j=0,1,2 = a 1 ≤ 1/ √ 2. In contrast, consider a channel with max{a j } j=0,1,2 = a 1 = 1/2 + δ &gt; 1/ √ 2, (δ &gt; 0). From the unitary constraints</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">3 k=1 u 2 kl = 3 l=1 u 2 kl = 1, one can derive a 2 0 u 2 31 + a 2 2 u 2 33 -a 2 1 u 2 32 = a 2 0 + a 2 2 -a 2 1 &lt; 0.</formula><p>This implies that our scheme is sufficient for any quantum channel satisfying max{a j } j=0,1,2 = a 1 ≤ 1/ √ 2. In particular, this analysis can be extended symmetrically to cases where a 0 or a 2 are maximal, thus exhaustively characterizing all perfect teleportation-capable channels. This completes the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. ENTANGLEMENT AND CLASSICAL INFORMATION</head><p>A perfect quantum teleportation scheme involves three key elements: establishing a quantum channel, the joint measurement performed by Alice, and the transmission of classical information to Bob. Each of these steps requires the consumption of certain resources. Our scheme provides a continuous region to explore these resources in the perfect teleportation of a qubit, where the Schmidt coefficients of the bipartite states can be selected at random. Also, by examining the three key elements mentioned above, we have compared our scheme with the one presented in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>The quantifiers of the above three resources have been mentioned in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which are</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">E(|Φ 23 ) = - 2 i=0 a 2 i log 2 a 2 i ,<label>(13a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">E 12 = 3 j=1 [P j+ E(|ψ j+ 12 ) + P j-E(|ψ j-12 )],<label>(13b)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_26">H 12 = - 3 j=1 (P j+ log 2 P j+ + P j-log 2 P j-),<label>(13c)</label></formula><p>where E(|Φ 23 ) is the entanglement entropy of the quantum channel, E 12 is the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement defined by the average of the bases, H 12 is the Shannon entropy of the distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. It is worth noting that (13b) can be derived by direct generalization in the work of Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The entanglement of the qubitqutrit states (Eq. ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)) can be presented as a monotone increasing function of the concurrence, which are</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">C(|ψ 1+ 12 ) = C(|ψ 2+ 12 ) = 4u</formula><p>2 12 (u 2 11 +u 2 13 ), C(|ψ 1-12 ) = C(|ψ 2-12 ) = 4u 2 22 (u 2 21 +u 2 23 ), C(|ψ 3± 12 ) = 2u 2 31 u 2 32 (1-cos δ 1 )+2u 2 31 u 2 33 (1cos δ 2 ) +2u 2 32 u 2 33 [1-cos(δ 1 +δ 2 )], (14) where cos δ 1 = -a 4 0 u 4 31 + a 4 1 u 4 32 -a 4 2 u 4 33 2a 2 0 a 2 1 u 2 31 u 2 32 , cos δ 2 = -a 4 0 u 4 31 + a 4 2 u 4 33 -a 4 1 u 4 32 2a 2 0 a 2 2 u 2 31 u 2 33 , cos(δ 1 + δ 2 ) = -a 4 1 u 4 32 + a 4 2 u 4 33 -a 4 0 u 4 31 2a 2 1 a 2 2 u 2 32 u 2 33</p><p>.</p><p>Next, we will list two special cases of quantum channels to clarify the properties of these three quantities.</p><p>Case I: a 0 = a 1 or a 2 = a 1 . Since the constraints are symmetric under the exchange of a 0 and a 2 , it is sufficient to analyze the case a 2 = a 1 without loss of generality. The scheme in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> for this case can give an analytical expression of the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">E ′ 12 =H   1+ 1 3 + 2 9 [cos ξ 1 +cos ξ 2 +cos(ξ 1 -ξ 2 )] 2   ,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">H(x) = -x log 2 x -(1 -x) log 2 (1 -x) is the binary entropy with ξ 1 = π -arccos 2a 4 1 -a 4 2 2a 4 1 and ξ 2 = π + arccos a 2 2 2a 2 1</formula><p>. contrast, our scheme involves more degrees of freedom ({θ j } j=1,2,3 , {δ j } j=1,2 ). The constraint a 2 = a 1 only partially restricts these parameters, necessitating a numerical exploration of the accessible entanglement regimes.</p><p>Case II:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">a 1 = 1/ √ 2.</formula><p>For this configuration, Ref.</p><p>[1] yields the entanglement measure</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">E ′ 12 =H   1+ 1 3 + 2 9 [cos ξ ′ 1 +cos ξ ′ 2 +cos(ξ ′ 1 -ξ ′ 2 )] 2   (16) with ξ ′ 1 = π -arccos a 4 0 +1/4-a 4 2 a 2 0 and ξ ′ 2 = π + arccos a 4 0 +a 4 2 -1/4 2a 2 0 a 2 2</formula><p>. In our scheme, although constrained by Eqs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and the condition a 1 = 1/ √ 2, the parameter space still cannot fully determine the relationship between parameters {θ j } j=1,2,3 and {δ j } j=1,2 , and the Schmidt coefficients {a j } j=0,1,2 . Consequently, numerical methods are required to determine the achievable entanglement regimes between Alice's joint measurement and the quantum channel.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2</ref> compares the entanglement degree relationships between Alice's joint measurement and the quantum channel: (a) results from Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> protocol, (b) our scheme's results (Sect. III). It is easy to find that the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement reaches its maximum when the quantum channel is maximally entangled, and approaches a minimum as any Schmidt coefficient a j=0,1,2 vanishes. In particular, our scheme achieves a superior lower bound. When any a j → 0, the entanglement degree of Alice's joint measurement yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">E 12 = 1 2 + 1 2 H( 3 4 ) ≈ 0.906 for our protocol, compared to E ′ 12 = H(<label>2</label></formula><p>3 ) ≈ 0.918 in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. One can also note that when the quantum channel entanglement is 1, the scheme in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is constrained to a unique protocol of Alice's joint measurement basis due to its fundamental design (omitting common phase factor). In contrast, our scheme provides flexible non-unique protocols (detailed examples are shown in the next section). Additionally, the region for case I in our scheme (red region in panel (b)) shows a non-monotonic relationship between the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement and the quantum channel. This demonstrates that the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement does not represent Alice's ability to utilize the quantum channel.</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref> shows the regions of the classical bits sent to Bob versus the entanglement of the quantum channel, along with the specific regions and curves for cases I and II. In the scheme of Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, the probabilities of Alice's outcome remain independent of the quantum channel, whereas our scheme demonstrates an overall upward trend between the classical communication cost and the entanglement of the quantum channel. When the quantum channel reduces to a two-qubit Bell state, the minimum number of classical bits required reaches its lower bound of 2 bits. This implies that our scheme contains the case of the two-qubit channel naturally. We will show this in the next section.</p><p>We observe that the sum of the average entanglement of Alice's measurement and the Shannon entropy of the classical information sent to Bob exhibits a trade-off relation: the greater the entanglement resource consumption in Alice's joint measurement, the lower the classical communication costs. By Eqs. (13b) and (13c), the upper bound of E 12 + H 12 can be easily obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">E 12 + H 12 ≤ 3 j=1 {P j+ [H( 1 + 1 -C j+ 2 ) + log 2 P j+ ] + P j-[H( 1 + 1 -C j- 2 ) + log 2 P j-]}<label>(17)</label></formula><p>with ). For a fixed quantum channel, the quantity E 12 + H 12 is upperbounded by a function of the Schmidt coefficient a 1 .</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">C 1+ = C 2+ = 1 -cos 4 θ 1 sin 4 θ 3 , C 1-= C 2-= 1 -sin 4</formula><p>A more physically significant bound is the lower bound on E 12 + H 12 , characterizing the minimal teleportation cost that Alice incurs when using the fixed quantum channel. This lower bound can be characterized as a piecewise function of the entanglement entropy of the quantum channel E(|Φ 23 ) = E:</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">E 12 + H 12 ≥ f 1 (E), E ∈ (1, 3 2 ) f 2 (E), E ∈ ( 3 2 , log 2 3) ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where f 1 (E) = g(q) = q + 3 q + 1 + 2 log 2 (q + 1)-2q + 1 (q + 1) 2 log 2 (2q + 1) -</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">q(2q + 1) (q + 1) 2 log 2 q, f 2 (E) = kE + b.</formula><p>Here, the parameter q exhibits a positive correlation with the entanglement entropy of the quantum channel E, obeying the relation H(q) = 2(E -1), and k = 5/3-log 2 3 log 2 3-3/2 , b = 2 log 2 3 + 11  6 -1 4 log 2 3-6 .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. SPECIFIC CASES</head><p>In this section, we will demonstrate through quantitative analysis of a specific case that our protocol exhibits non-uniqueness when the two-qutrit channel degenerates to a two-qubit scenario. Remarkably, Cases I and II produce identical entanglement measurement regions in this limit. We therefore focus on Case I to streamline our discussion.</p><p>The degeneracy of channel dimensions emerges when any Schmidt coefficient approaches zero. As a prototypical example, we analyze case I under the condition a 0 = 0, where the first term in the Schmidt decomposition of the two-qutrit channel vanishes. Under this condition, Alice's joint measurement basis reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">|ψ 1+ 12 = cos θ 1 |00 + sin θ 1 √ 2 (-|11 + |02 ), |ψ 1-12 = sin θ 1 |00 + cos θ 1 √ 2 (|11 -|02 ), |ψ 2+ 12 = cos θ 1 |10 - sin θ 1 √ 2 (|01 + |12 ), |ψ 2-12 = sin θ 1 |10 + cos θ 1 √ 2 (|01 + |12 ), |ψ 3± 12 = 1 2 [(|11 + |02 ) ± (|01 -|12 )]<label>(19)</label></formula><p>with</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">θ 1 ∈ [0, π/2], or |ψ 1+ 12 = cos θ 2 |00 + sin θ 2 √ 2 (|11 + |02 ), |ψ 1-12 = 1 √ 2 (|11 + |02 ), |ψ 2+ 12 = cos θ 2 |10 + sin θ 2 √ 2 (|01 -|12 ), |ψ 2-12 = 1 √ 2 (|01 -|12 ), |ψ 3± 12 = [- sin θ 2 √ 2 |00 + cos θ 2 2 (|11 + |02 )] ± [- sin θ 2 √ 2 |10 + cos θ 2 2 (|01 -|12 )]<label>(20)</label></formula><p>with θ 2 ∈ [0, π/2]. Since the above two sets of measurement bases cannot be transformed into each other through a local unitary transformation, it is easy to get non-unique teleportation protocols through our scheme.</p><p>For simplicity, we assume that Alice performs her measurements in the form of Eq. 19. Then the probabilities of Alice's outcome and the entanglement of Alice's joint measurement can be given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">P 1+ =P 2+ = sin 2 θ 1 4 , P 1-=P 2-= cos 2 θ 1 4 , P 3± = 1 4 ,<label>(21a)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">E 12 = 1 2 1+sin 2 θ 1 H( 1+cos 2 θ 1 2 )+cos 2 θ 1 H( 1+sin 2 θ 1 2 ) ,<label>(21b)</label></formula><p>where H(x) is the binary entropy mentioned above. Further, the Shannon entropy of the distribution (21) is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">H 12 =2- 1 2 (sin 2 θ 1 log 2 sin 2 θ 1 +cos 2 θ 1 log 2 cos 2 θ 1 ). (<label>22</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_42">)</formula><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref> shows the relationship between the total resources that Alice costs (E 12 +H 12 ) and the parameter θ 1 . The minimum of E 12 +H 12 occurs when θ 1 = 0 or π/2. In this scenario, the measurement of qubit 1 and qutrit 2 in bases |ψ 1+ 12 and |ψ 2+ 12 (with θ 1 = 0) or |ψ 1-12 and |ψ 2-12 (with θ 1 = π/2) does not collapse qutrit 3 into the form of α|φ α + β|φ β . This implies that our scheme reduces to two-qubit Bell state teleportation. Therefore, the entanglement of Alice's measurement and the Shannon entropy of the distribution are E 12 = 1 and H 12 = 2, respectively. In addition, the maximum of E 12 + H 12 occurs when θ 1 = π/4. In this case, the measurement collapses the initial state |φ 1 |Φ 23 as with the probabilities P 1± = P 2± = 1/8 and P 3± = 1/4. The entanglement of Alice's measurement and the Shannon entropy of the distribution are E 12 = 1 2 [1 + H( 3 4 )] ≈ 0.906 and H 12 = 2 + 1 2 log 2 1 2 = 5 2 .</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">|φ 1± 3 = ± 1 2 √ 2 (α|2 -β|1 ) 3 , |φ 2± 3 = ∓ 1 2 √ 2 (α|1 + β|2 ) 3 , |φ 3± 3 = 1 2 √ 2 [α(|1 ± |2 ) + β(±|1 -|2 )] 3<label>(23)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. SUMMARY</head><p>By extending an equivalent scheme for the original teleportation protocol using the two-qubit channel, we propose a scheme for perfect teleportation utilizing the partially entangled two-qutrit channel. For any partially entangled two-qutrit channel that satisfies the perfect teleportation condition, it is sufficient and necessary to propose a teleportation protocol using our scheme. Compared with the scheme in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, our scheme consumes fewer classical and quantum resources for the same channel. In addition, our scheme is suitable for a wider channel range than the scheme in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. We also establish a trade-off relation between the entanglement of Alice's measurement and the classical information sent to Bob, which quantifies the lower bound of these two quantities.</p><p>Notably, our scheme faces limitations when extended to higher-dimensional channels. The primary challenge stems from the exponentially growing complexity (scaling as ∼ 2 da/2-1 ) in constructing Alice's measurement basis, as the number of orthogonal subspace decompositions increases with the system dimension d a . This raises a fundamental question: Does there exist a class of teleportation protocols where (i) high-dimensional joint measurements can be realized through simple low-dimensional extensions, while (ii) maintaining analogous resource trade-offs, and (iii) preserving universality for all perfectteleportation-enabled channels? Addressing this question represents a promising direction for future research.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>FIG. 1. The quantum circuit diagram shows that qubit teleportation is realized with Alice's (top two wires) and Bob's (bottom wire) subsystems. The single lines denote qubits, and the double lines denote classical bits.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,74.79,52.09,203.12,56.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>, |10 , |11 }, where u kl , v kl (k, l = 1, 2) and η are real numbers with k u kl = l u kl = k v kl = l v kl = 1. In other words, Alice's measurement basis is derived from two unitary operators U = 2 k,l=1 u kl | k l| and V = 2 p,q=1 v pq • e iδ(p-1) |p q| acting on the subspaces of {| k , | l } = {|00 , |11 } and {|p , |q } = {|10 , |01 }, respectively. The unitary D 12 sends the initial state |φ 1 |Φ 23 to D † 12 |φ 1 |Φ 23 = |00 12 |φ 1+ 3 + |01 12 |φ 2+ 3 + |10 12 |φ 1-3 + |11 12 |φ 2-3 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>iδ2 u 31 cos ζ u 32 e iδ1 sin ζ u 33 cos ζ u 31 sin ζ u 32 cos ζ u 33 e iδ2 sin ζ iδ2 -u 31 sin ζ u 32 e iδ1 cos ζ -u 33 sin ζ u 31 cos ζ -u 32 sin ζ u 33 e iδ2 cos ζ , |02 , |10 , |11 , |12 }. Similarly to the case of two-qubit channel, this unitary operation is equivalent to performing a joint measurement of qubits 1 and 2 in the orthonormal basis |ψ j± 12 = j ′ -1, j -1| 12 D 12 with j ′ = 1, 2 and j = 1, 2, 3. Perfect quantum teleportation requires sin 2 ζ = cos 2 ζ = 1/2, where we may take sin ζ = cos ζ = 1/ √ 2 by convention. In this sense, after performing the above measurements on qubit 1 and qutrit 2, Alice's actions caused Bob's qutrit 3 to collapse into the state |φ j± 3 = α|φ α 3 + β|φ β 3 , which are</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIG. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>FIG. 2. Entanglement degree regimes for Alice's joint measurement and the quantum channel. (a) Results from Ref. [1] scheme: red curve (case I) and magenta curve (case II). (b) Our proposed scheme (Section III): red region (case I) and magenta region (case II). In addition, more specific parameter configurations are shown in (b). The blue curve shows case I with θ2 = π/4, θ3 ∈ [0, π/4] and θ1 = 1 2 arctan(-√ 2 cot 2θ3). The green curve shows case II with θ1 = π/4, θ2 = 0 and θ3 ∈ [arcsin 1/3, π/4].</figDesc><graphic coords="5,74.79,190.59,203.32,127.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>FIG. 3. The classical bits sent to Bob vs. the entanglement of the quantum channel. The regions and curves of different colors correspond one-to-one with the various cases in Fig. 1b.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,337.89,52.09,203.12,132.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>θ 1 sin 4 θ 3 , 1 2</head><label>31</label><figDesc>C 3± = cos 2 θ 3 (1 + sin 2 θ 3 ), andP 1+ = P 2+ = sin 2 θ1+cos 2 θ1 cos 2 θ3 4+2 cos 2θ3 , P 1-= P 2-= cos 2 θ3+cos 2 θ1 sin 2 θ3 4+2 cos 2θ3 , P 3± = cos 2 θ34+2 cos 2θ3 , where θ 1 = arctan(-√ 2 cot 2θ 3 ), and θ 3 = 1 2 arccos(</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIG. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>FIG.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref>. The relationship between the total resources that Alice costs and the parameter θ1 when a0 = 0.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>VII. ACKNOWLEDGEMENT J. L. C. was supported by the <rs type="funder">Innovation Program for Quantum Science and Technology</rs> (Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">2024ZD0301000</rs>), and the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundation of China</rs> (Grant No. <rs type="grantNumber">12275136</rs>). F. L. Z. was supported by the <rs type="funder">National Natural Science Foundations of China</rs> (Grants Nos. <rs type="grantNumber">11675119</rs>). D. Z. was supported by the <rs type="funder">Nankai Zhide Foundations</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_RJ6gaAb">
					<idno type="grant-number">2024ZD0301000</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_tuDmVDu">
					<idno type="grant-number">12275136</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_Tkq3c9v">
					<idno type="grant-number">11675119</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Faithful teleportation with partially entangled states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gour</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teleporting an unknown quantum state via dual classical and einstein-podolskyrosen channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brassard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Crépeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jozsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wootters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1895</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic teleportation and entanglement matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-C</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal quantum teleportation with an arbitrary pure state</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Banaszek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal conclusive teleportation of quantum states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Delgado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fuentes-Guridi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22310</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal teleportation with a mixed state of two qubits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Verstraete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Verschelde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97901</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic teleportation without loss of information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Roa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Groiseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12344</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum teleportation in high dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-H</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-S</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Erhard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L.-C</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krenn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N.-L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Y</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">70505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum teleportation via qutrit entangled state</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. J. Electron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental high-dimensional quantum teleportation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-M</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-J</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W.-B</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-X</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">230501</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perfect teleportation with a partially entangled quantum channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F.-L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32430</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic resumable quantum teleportation in high dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F.-L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chin. Phys. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">30302</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum teleportation using three-particle entanglement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bourennane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4394</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Control power in perfect controlled teleportation via partially entangled channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">52305</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum repeaters based on atomic ensembles and linear optics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sangouard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>De Riedmatten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reviews of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum cryptographic network based on quantum memories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Biham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Huttner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2651</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiparticle generalization of entanglement swapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vedral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">822</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum cryptography on multiuser optical fibre networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Townsend</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tarifi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:quant-ph/0401076</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
