<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">POWER OPTIMIZED PROGRAMMABLE EMBEDDED CONTROLLER</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kamaraju</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Dept. of ECE</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gudlavalleru Engineering College</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Gudlavalleru</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lal Kishore</surname></persName>
							<email>lalkishorek@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Director,SIT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jawarlal Nehru Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hyderabad</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="middle">A V N</forename><surname>Tilak</surname></persName>
							<email>avntilak@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of ECE</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Gudlavalleru Engineering College</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Gudlavalleru</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">POWER OPTIMIZED PROGRAMMABLE EMBEDDED CONTROLLER</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B7DC9699C0A5B36F5EACF22A783ED17C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.5121/ijcnc.2010.2409</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-07T10:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Power</term>
					<term>Clock Gating</term>
					<term>RISC</term>
					<term>FPGA</term>
					<term>Xilinx</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Now a days, power has become a primary consideration in hardware design, and is critical in computer systems especially for portable devices with high performance and more functionality. Clock-gating is the most common technique used for reducing processor's power. In this work clock gating technique is applied to optimize the power of fully programmable Embedded Controller (PEC) employing RISC architecture. The CPU designed supports i) smart instruction set, ii) I/O port, UART iii) on-chip clocking to provide a range of frequencies , iv) RISC as well as controller concepts. The whole design is captured using VHDL and is implemented on FPGA chip using Xilinx .The architecture and clock gating technique together is found to reduce the power consumption by 33.33% of total power consumed by this chip.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Low power consumption in embedded systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> has become a key factor for many applications. Portable applications, needing long battery life together with high peak-performance, are demanding a very careful design at all levels.</p><p>The most important factor contributing to the energy consumption is the switching activity <ref type="bibr">[2] [3]</ref> .Once the technology and supply voltage have been set , major energy savings come from the careful minimization of switching activity.</p><p>While some switching activity is functional, i.e. it is required to propagate and manipulate information; there is a substantial amount of unnecessary activity in almost all digital circuits. Unnecessary switching activity arises from spurious transitions <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> due to unequal propagation delays (glitches) and transitions occurring within units that are not participating in a computation. One way to avoid these activities is by dynamically turning off the clock <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> to unused logic or peripherals .</p><p>Existing microprocessors <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, especially in the category of microcontrollers, often have the capability of partially gating the clock signal when they fetch and execute NOP or other minimal-activity instructions and also when a peripheral is powered-down. This does not totally eliminate spurious power consumption. Other processors <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> can enter low-power operating modes, disabling the clock signal generator (Xtal oscillator and PLL). However, this is not totally efficient in important applications. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> optimization of power is achieved by taking assistance of compiler while executing instructions. However hardware approach proposed in this work reduces the power without compromising speed performance of the chip.</p><p>In the proposed PEC, the control unit is designed to have the capability of gating the clock signal when they fetch and execute instructions. On-chip clocking <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> mechanism is employed to synchronize with on-chip peripherals/memory and with the external bus. For power optimization of integrated circuits it is relevant to understand the causes of power dissipation. Clock power <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> dominates the total power consumed by a microcontroller as the clock is fed to most of the circuit blocks. Charge/discharge power given by P = f C L V dd V s, dominates the total power dissipation of the chip. The frequency f of the clock cannot be reduced as it effects the speed of the chip. When output swings from 0 to V dd then P varies as square V dd .However lowering P by reducing power supply voltage to 2V or less is found to lead to several problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> [12] like decrease in drivability of MOSFET and increase in gate delay time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PROGRAMMABLE EMBEDDED CONTROLLER ARCHITECTURE</head><p>Architecture of PEC is shown in Figure .1. Various blocks in the architecture are register file, ALU, RAM, ROM, UART, I/O Ports, BCD to 7 segment driver , Control unit, and clocker, designed to perform particular task. Register File is a set of registers that are modeled as RAM of 16 bit words, used to store intermediate values during instruction processing. The ALU performs 16 bit operations. The Read Only Memory (ROM) is 256 bytes with 16 bit word length and is used to store the instruction data. The Random Access Memory (RAM) 1K×16 is used to store temporary data. Port 0 and Port 1 are two ports which are configured as output and input ports respectively.</p><p>A display driver for BCD to 7 segment display is designed to drive the 7 segment display unit. The control unit generates various control signals to all other blocks to execute desired task specified by the instructions. The PEC is initiated by the reset signal whenever reset signal asserts high, the controller generate appropriate signals to load the PC address of the ROM. The external interrupt mechanism activates on any hardware interrupt or reset signal arriving at the controller when it is in idle mode.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">On-Chip Clocking Mechanism</head><p>The frequency of the application specific hardwired oscillator shown in Figure    The controller shown in Figure.1 supports predefined smart instruction set having length of 16 bits each. Gated clock signal generated by the control unit allows the clock to be fed only to the active blocks and not to the unused blocks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Clock Gating</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Control Unit</head><p>The control unit provides all of control signals to regulate the data traffic and necessary signals to perform the desired functions. The control unit architecture contain a state machine that causes all appropriate signal values to update based on current state and input signals and produce a next state for state machine. The control unit performs two processes. The first is a combinational process (not clocked) that examines the current state and all inputs and produces output control signals and next state output. The second is the sequential process (having a clock) that is used to store the current state and copy of the next state to the current state. By implementing the instructions given in the instruction set (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) does not cause any functional limitation, but enables an effective way of power saving through generation of gated clock signals. All the instructions are of length 2 bytes and of direct addressing mode type. Instruction set includes Load, Store, Branch, ALU and Shift instructions.</p><p>Control Unit Table 1 Instruction Set OPCODE INSTRUCTION DESCRIPTION 00000 NOP No operation 00001 LOAD Load register 00010 STORE Store the register 00011 MOVE Move the value into the register 00100 LOADI Load the register with immediate value 00101 BI Branch to immediate address 00110 BGTI Branch greater than to immediate address 00111 INC Increment 01000 DEC Decrement 01001 AND Logical AND two registers 01010 OR Logical OR two register 01011 XOR Logical XOR two register 01100 NOT Logical NOT the register 01101 ADD Add two registers 01110 SUB Subtract two registers 01111 ZERO Zero a register 10000 PORT0 Port 0 write 10001 BLT Branch lass than 10010 BNEQ Branch not equal 10011 PORT1 Port 1 read 10100 BGT Branch greater than 10110 BCH Branch all the time 10111 BEQ Branch if equal 11000 B7S 7 segment driver 11001 BLTE Branch less than or equal 11010 SHL Shift left 11011 SHR Shift right 11100 ROR Rotate right 11101 ROL Rotate lrft 11110 UARTS UART sel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS</head><p>The entire design is captured in VHDL and simulated using Xilinx tool. The simulation results of control unit are presented in Figure.  Figure.6 Control Unit Simulation Results (contd…) Figure.6 Control Unit Simulation Results (contd…) Figure.7 Control Unit RTL Schematic Figure.8 Top Level Module Simulation Results Figure.9 Top Level Module RTL Schematic</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Power Analysis</head><p>The estimation of power consumption of each module is done using Xilinx Xpower's tool. The graphical representation of power consumed in various modules is shown in Figure .10. 33.33%  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Characteristics of the Chip</head><p>The characteristics of the designed chip are</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The need for low power systems is being driven by many market segments. There are several approaches to reducing the power. In this work clock gating technique is applied to optimize the power of fully programmable embedded controller employing RISC architecture. The whole design is captured using VHDL language and is implemented on FPGA chip using Xilinx .The chip has less hardware complexity as this works based on single addressing mode to access the data for processing. The architecture and clock gating technique together have reduced the power consumption by 33.33% of total power consumed by the chip. This clock gating technique can be applied from chip level to module and then eventually to systems.</p><p>Architecture RISC Optimization Power Instructions 2 byte ROM 256 bytes RAM 1 KB ALU 16 bit Power Supply 2.4V Power Dissipation 3.62mW/MHz</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>.2 is programmable by means of the 4-bit number (control word value) contained in the dedicated register r_osc. On-chip clocking is used to obtain different frequencies ranging from 44 MHz to 134 MHz by changing the control word values as shown in Figure.3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure.1 Architecture of Programmable Embedded Controller</figDesc><graphic coords="3,105.72,79.80,414.84,279.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure.4(a)  shows the schematic of latch element. A significant amount of power is consumed during charge/discharge cycle of the cumulative gate capacitance C g of the latch, when the clock is fed directly and there is no change in the clock cycle<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Figure. 4(b) shows the latch with gated clock. By gating the clock [14] [15] , charge/discharge of C g can be effected only when there is change in the clock cycle thus saving power.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,207.24,424.92,245.28,145.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure.4 Schematic of Latch Element (a) without clock gating (b) with clock gating</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure.5 Signals of Control Unit If the reset signal is high the sequential process set the current state value to reset1, the first state of the reset sequence. The logic for clock gating is implemented within the control unit. The controller generate appropriate clock gating signal to reduce power consumption of the chip. When the control unit decodes the opcode of the instruction, the control unit generates control signals as shown in Figure.5, to execute the instruction.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,247.92,150.60,204.48,343.68" type="vector_box" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><figDesc>6.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure.6 Control Unit Simulation Results</figDesc><graphic coords="7,105.72,299.76,423.00,170.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure. 10</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure.10 Power Analysis Total power consumption is estimated to be 273mW without clock gating and only 182 mW after clock gating technique is employed, thus achieving a power saving of 33.33% (Figure.11).</figDesc><graphic coords="9,167.76,473.52,295.56,177.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure. 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure.11 Comparison of Power Consumed without and with Clock Gating</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,105.72,79.80,423.00,192.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,105.72,308.40,417.96,151.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="8,105.72,496.92,423.60,183.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Decomposed Architecture of Low Power Embedded Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Haris</forename><surname>Lekatsas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jorg</forename><surname>Henkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wayne</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 2000 IEEE International Conference on Computer Design: VLSI in Computer and Processors</title>
		<meeting>of the 2000 IEEE International Conference on Computer Design: VLSI in Computer and essors</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clock-Gating and Its Application to Low Power Design of Sequential Circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Qing</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Massoud</forename><surname>Pedram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xunwei</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems-1: Fundamental Theory and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-03">March 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Power Considerations in the Design of the Alpha 21264 Microprocessor, Transaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Larry</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Biro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID: 1998 ACM 0-89791-964-5/98/06</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="731" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-Power Clock Distribution Using Multiple Voltages and Reduced Swings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jatuchai</forename><surname>Pangjun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sachin</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Saptnekar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Very Large Scale Integration(VLSI) Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="318" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-06">June 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wattch:A Framework for Architectural-Level Power Analysis and Optimizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vivek</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Margaret</forename><surname>Martonosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID:ACM 2000 1-58113-232-8/00/6</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Transaction</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Novel Low -Power Micoprcessor Architecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rolf</forename><surname>Hakenes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yiannos</forename><surname>Manoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Trans. Id: 0-7695-0801-4/00 $10.00</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low Power Design for Embedded Processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bill</forename><surname>Moyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. of IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11">November 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hardware -Assisted Run -Time Monitoring for secure Program Execution on Embedded processors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Divya</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Srivaths</forename><surname>Ravi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anand</forename><surname>Raghunathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Niraj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1307" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-12">December 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power Minimization using Control Generated Clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Srikanth</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">DAC 2000</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Angeles, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Clock Gating Technique for Energy Reduction in Portable Computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sulaiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Computer and Communication Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05">2008. May 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="842" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survey of Optimization Techniques Targeting Low Power VLSI circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Srinivas</forename><surname>Devadas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sharad</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">32 nd ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low Power Electronics and Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Brock</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Massoud</forename><surname>Pedram</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Very Large Scale Integration (VLSI) Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-12">December 1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Clock Power Model to Evaluate Impact of Architectural and Technology Optimizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vijaykrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mary</forename><forename type="middle">Jane</forename><surname>Irwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Very Large Scale Integration (VLSI) Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="855" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-12">December 2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clock-Tree Power Optimization based on RTL Clock-Gating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monica</forename><surname>Donno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alessandro</forename><surname>Ivaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Luca</forename><surname>Benini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Enrico</forename><surname>Macii</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">DAC 2003</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="622" to="627" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconfigurable Design with Clock Gating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Osborne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Luk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G F</forename><surname>Coutinho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Mencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>978-1-4244-1985-2/08</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transaction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">He had published more than 76 research papers in International/Natioanl journals and presented papers in International / National Conferences.He is best teacher awardee from the Government of Andhrapardesh,S.V.C.Aiya Memorial Award from IETE,Merit Award from DEC, Ethopia, Bapu Seetharam Memorial Award from IETE and has many other academic distinctions to his credit.He wrote books on Electronic Devices,Circuit Analysis,Linear IC Applications,Electronic Measurements and Instrumentation and VLSI Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Authors Dr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kishore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Tilak, obtained Master&apos;s degree from Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur and Ph.D. from Indian Institute of Technology, Madras during 1984 and 1997 respectively</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>D. from Indian Institute of Science (IISC) Bangalore</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>obtained Master&apos;s degree and Ph He is a Fellow of Institution of Electronics And Telecommunication Engineers, India and Life Member of Indian Society for Technical Education</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">obtained his Bachelor&apos;s degree &amp; Master&apos;s degree from Andhra University. Areas of interest are Microprocessors, Microcontrollers, Embedded Systems, Low Power VLSI. He is a fellow of Institution of Electronics and Telecommunication Engineers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kamaraju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>India &amp; Member of VSI</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
