<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Floorplanning of VLSI by Mixed-Variable Optimization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2024-01-27">27 Jan 2024</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jian</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Huabin</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Basic Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuchang Shouyi University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430064</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jian</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhanyang</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Information Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Yu</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<email>ychen@whut.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wuhan University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430070</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Floorplanning of VLSI by Mixed-Variable Optimization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2024-01-27">27 Jan 2024</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9999580326B3163CD2BCC5F14DE2209A</idno>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2401.15317v1[cs.NE]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T12:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>VLSI</term>
					<term>floorplanning</term>
					<term>distribution evolutionary algorithm</term>
					<term>conjugate sub-gradient algorithm</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>By formulating the floorplanning of VLSI as a mixed-variable optimization problem, this paper proposes to solve it by memetic algorithms, where the discrete orientation variables are addressed by the distribution evolutionary algorithm based on a population of probability model (DEA-PPM), and the continuous coordination variables are optimized by the conjugate sub-gradient algorithm (CSA). Accordingly, the fixed-outline floorplanning algorithm based on CSA and DEA-PPM (FFA-CD) and the floorplanning algorithm with golden section strategy (FA-GSS) are proposed for the floorplanning problems with and without fixed-outline constraint. Numerical experiments on GSRC test circuits show that the proposed algorithms are superior to some celebrated B*tree based floorplanning algorithms, and are expected to be applied to large-scale floorplanning problems due to their low time complexity.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Floorplanning is a critical stage in the physical design of very large-scale integration circuit (VLSI) that determines the performance of VLSI chips to a large extent <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. It is a complex optimization problem with multiple objectives and constraints, which makes it challenging to develop high-performance algorithms for floorplanning of VLSI <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Floorplanning algorithms generally fall into two categories: the floorplanning algorithm based on combinatorial optimization model (FA-COM) and the floorplanning algorithm based on analytic optimization model (FA-AOM). Representing the relative positions of macros by combinatorial coding structures such as the B*-tree, the sequential pair, etc., one can formulate the floorplanning problem as a combinatorial optimization problem, which is then addressed by metaheuristics in the FA-COMs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. The combinatorial codes representing relative positions of macros can be naturally decoded into the compact floorplans complying with the non-overlapping constraints, however, the combinatorial explosion contributes to poor performances of FA-COM on large-scale cases. Accordingly, the problem size could be reduced by clustering or partitioning strategies, which in turn makes it hard to converge to the global optimal results of the investigated large-scale floorplanning problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>FA-AOMs address analytical floorplanning models by continuous optimization algorithms, which contributes to their lower time complexities on large-scale cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. Since the optimization results of continuous optimization algorithms do not fulfill the non-overlapping constraints for most cases, a FA-AOM usually consists of the global floorplanning stage and the legalization stage, the first optimizing the overall evaluation index, and the second tuning the positions of macros to eliminate constraint violations of results. Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> proposed an analytic floorplanning algorithm for large-scale floorplanning cases, where the fixedoutline global floorplanning was implemented by optimizing the electrostatic field model of global placement. In the legalization stage, horizontal constraint graphs and vertical constraint graphs were constructed to eliminate overlap of floorplanning results. Huang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> presented an improved electrostatics-based analytical method for fixed-outline floorplanning, which incorporates module rotation and sizing driven by wirelength.</p><p>Since some of the evaluation indexes of global floorplanning are not smooth, additional smooth approximation to the optimization objective function could be incorporated to achieve fast convergence of gradient-based optimization algorithms. However, the approximation procedure not only introduces extra time complexity of the FA-AOM, but also leads to its local convergence to an optimal solution significantly different from that of the original non-smooth model. Accordingly, the conjugate subgradient algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> is employed in this paper to deal with the continuous variables representing coordinates of modules. Meanwhile, we address the orientation of modules by discrete variables, and formulate the floorplanning problem as a mixed-variable optimization problem.</p><p>Rest of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 introduces some preliminaries. Then, the proposed algorithms developed for floorplanning problems with and without fixed-outline constraints are presented in Sections 3 and 4, respectively. Numerical experiment is performed in Section 5 to demonstrate the competitiveness of the proposed algorithms, and Section 6 concludes this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Preliminaries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Problem Statement</head><p>Given a collection of rectangular modules V = {v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v n } and a set of edges (networks) E = {e 1 , e 2 , . . . , e m }, the VLSI floorplanning problem tries to minimize the total wirelength and the floorplan area by placing modules in approximate positions. Denote the center coordinates of module v i be (x i , y i ), and its orientation is represented by r i . A floorplan of VLSI is represented by the combination of vectors x, y and r, where x = (x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x n ), y = (y 1 , y 2 , . . . , y n ), r = (r 1 , r 2 , . . . , r n ). Subject to the constraint of placing non-overlaping modules with a fixed outline, the floorplanning problem is formulated as min W (x, y)</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">s.t. D(x, y, r) = 0, B(x, y, r) = 0,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where W (x, y) is the total wirelength, D(x, y, r) is the sum of overlapping area, and B(x, y, r) is the sum of width beyond the fixed outline. By the Lagrange multiplier method, it can be transformed into an unconstrained optimization model</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">min f (x, y, r) = αW (x, y) + λ D(x, y, r) + µB(x, y, r),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where α, λ, and µ are parameters to be confirmed. Here, the square root of D(x, y, r) is adopted to ensure that all indexes to be minimized are of the same dimension.</p><p>Total Wirelength W (x, y) : The total wirelength is here taken as the total sum of half-perimeter wirelength (HWPL)</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">W (x, y) = e∈E (max vi∈e x i -min vi∈e x i + max vi∈e y i -min vi∈e y i )<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Sum of Overlapping Area D(x, y, r) : The sum of overlapping area is computed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D(x, y, r) = i,j O i,j (x, r) × O i,j (y, r),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where O i,j (x, r) and O i,j (y, r) represent the overlapping lengths of modules i and j in the X-axis and Y -axis directions, respectively. Denoting ∆ x (i, j) = |x ix j |, we know</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">O i,j (x, r) =      max( ŵi , ŵj ), if 0 ≤ ∆ x (i, j) ≤ | ŵi-ŵj| 2 , ŵi-2∆x(i,j)+ ŵj 2 , if | ŵi-ŵj | 2 &lt; ∆ x (i, j) ≤ ŵi+ ŵj 2 , 0, if ŵi+ ŵj 2 &lt; ∆ x (i, j),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where ŵi is confirmed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ŵi = w i , if r i ∈ {0, π}, h i , otherwise, i ∈ {1, 2 . . . , n}.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Denoting ∆ y (i, j) = |y iy j |, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">O i,j (y, r) =        max( ĥi , ĥj ), if 0 ≤ ∆ y (i, j) ≤ | ĥi-ĥj | 2 , ĥi-2∆y(i,j)+ ĥj 2 , if | ĥi-ĥj | 2 &lt; ∆ y (i, j) ≤ ĥi+ ĥj 2 , 0, if ĥi+ ĥj 2 &lt; ∆ y (i, j),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where ĥi is confirmed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ĥi = h i , if r i ∈ {0, π}, w i , otherwise, i ∈ {1, 2 . . . , n}.<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Sum of Width beyond the Fixed Outline B(x, y, r) : For floorplanning problems with fixed-outline, the positions of modules must meet the following constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">0 ≤ x i -ŵi /2, x i + ŵi /2 ≤ W * , 0 ≤ y i -ĥi /2, y i + ĥi /2 ≤ H * ,</formula><p>where W * and H * are the width and the height of square outline, respectively. Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">b 1,i (x) = max(0, ŵi /2 -x i ), b 2,i (x) = max(0, ŵi /2 + x i -W * ), b 1,i (y) = max(0, ĥi /2 -y i ), b 2,i (y) = max 0, ĥi /2 + y i -H * ),</formula><p>ŵi and ĥi are confirmed by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">6</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">8</ref>), respectively. Accordingly, B(x, y, r) can be confirmed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">B(x, y, r) = n i=1 (b 1,i (x) + b 2,i (x) + b 1,i (y) + b 2,i (y)),<label>(9)</label></formula><p>which is smoothed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">B(x, y, r) = n i=1 (b 2 1,i (x) + b 2 2,i (x) + b 2 1,i (y) + b 2 2,i (y)).<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Let β = 0, we get for legitimization of the global floorplanning result the optimization problem min f (x, y, r) = λ 0 D(x, y, r) + µ 0 B(x, y, r).</p><p>(11)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The Conjugate Sub-gradient Algorithm for Optimization of the Coordinate</head><p>Zhu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> proposed to solving the non-smooth continuous optimization model of the global placement by the conjugate sub-gradient algorithm (CSA). With an initial solution u 0 , the pseudo code of CSA is presented in Algorithm 1. Because the CSA is not necessarily gradient-descendant, the step size has a significant influence on its convergence performance. The step size is determined by the norm of the conjugate directions together with the control parameter s k , which is updated as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">s k = qs k-1 .</formula><p>As an initial study, we set q = 0.997 in this paper.</p><p>The termination-condition 1 is satisfied if k is greater than a given budget k max or several consecutive iterations fails to get a better solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The Distribution Evolutionary Algorithm for Optimization of the Orientation</head><p>Besides the coordinate vectors x and y, the floorplan is also confirmed by the orientation vectors r. The orientation of modules is confirmed by clockwise rotation, and we set r i = j if the rotation angle is θ i = jπ/2, j = 0, 1, 2, 3,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Algorithm 1: u * = CSA(f, u 0 , k max , s 0 ) Input: Objective function f (u), Initial solution u0, Maximum iterations kmax, Initial step control parameter s0; Output: Optimal solution u * ; 1 g0 ∈ ∂f (u0), d0 = 0, k ← 1; 2 while termination-condition 1 is not satisfied do 3 calculated subgradient g k ∈ ∂f (u k-1 ); 4 calculate Polak-Ribiere parameters η k = g T k (g k -g k-1 ) ||g k-1 || 2 2 ; 5 computed conjugate directions d k = -g k + η k d k-1 ; 6 calculating step size a k = s k-1 /||d k ||2; 7 renewal solution u k = u k-1 + a k d k ; 8 update step control parameters s k = qs k-1 ; 9 updata u * ; 10 end i = 1, . . . , n.</formula><p>The, optimization of the orientation vectors contributes to a combinatorial optimization problem. The estimation of distribution algorithm (EDA) is a kind of metaheuristics that can address the combinatorial optimization problem well, but its balance between global exploration and local exploitation is a challenging issue <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Xu et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> proposed for the graph coloring problem a distribution evolutionary algorithm based on a population of probability model (DEA-PPM), where a novel probability model and the associated orthogonal search are introduced to achieve well convergence performance on large-scale combinatorial problems.</p><p>The core idea of DEA-PPM for floorplanning is to simulate the probability distribution of orientations by constructing a probability matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">q = ( q 1 , . . . , q n ) =     q 11 q 12 • • • q 1n q 21 q 22 • • • q 2n q 31 q 32 • • • q 3n q 41 q 42 • • • q 4n     ,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where q j representing the probability that module j satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">|| q j || 2 2 = k i=1 q 2 ij = 1, ∀j = 1, . . . , n.<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Then, the random initialization of q generates a distribution matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">q(0) =     1/2 1/2 • • • 1/2 1/2 1/2 • • • 1/2 1/2 1/2 • • • 1/2 1/2 1/2 • • • 1/2     . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_17">)</formula><p>The implementation of DEA-PPM is based on distributed population Q(t) = (q [1] , . . . , q [np] ) and solution population P (t) = (p [1] , . . . , p [np] ), which are em-ployed here for the probability distributions and instantiations of orientation, respectively. Global convergence of DEA-PPM is achieved by an orthogonal search on Q(t), and the local exploitation are implemented in both the distribution space and the solution space.</p><p>3 The Fixed-outline Floorplanning Algorithm Based on CSA and DEA-PPM</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Framework</head><p>In this paper, the fixed-outline floorplanning algorithm based on CSA and DEA-PPM (FFA-CD) is proposed to solve the problem of fixed-outline floorplanning, where the DEA-PPM is employed to optimize the orientations of the modules and the CSA is used to optimize the corresponding coordinates of the modules. The framework of FFA-CD is presented in Algorithm 2. It starts with initialization of the distribution and solution populations Q(0) and P (0), where P (0) consists of orientation combinations of modules. Meanwhile, the corresponding population X and Y of module coordinate is initialized by Latin hypercube sampling <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Combining the orientation and coordinates of modules, we get the best coordinate vectors x * and y * , as well as the corresponding orientation vector r * . Then, the while loop of DEA-PPM is implemented to update Q(t) and P (t), where the CSA is deployed in UpdateXY to get the best module coordinate.</p><p>Algorithm 2: FFA-CD Input: f (x, y, r), f (x, y, r). Output: Optimal coordinate vector (x * , y * ) and orientation vector r * . 1 initialize the step control parameter s; 2 initialize Q(0) by ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">14</ref>), and generate P (0) by sampling Q(0); 3 initialize X and Y by Latin hypercube sampling; 4 let (x * , y * , p * ) = arg min f (x, y, r), x ∈ X, y ∈ Y , r ∈ P (0); set q * as the distribution q corresponding to p * ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">5 set t ← 1, α ← 1, λ ← 20, µ ← 100, λ0 ← 1, µ0 ← 10, kmax ← 50; 6 while termination-condition 2 is not satisfied do 7 Q ′ (t) = OrthExpQ(Q(t -1), P (t -1));P ′ (t) = SampleP (Q(t), P (t -1));(P (t), X, Y , s) = U pdateXY (P ′ (t), X, Y , s);Q(t) = Ref ineQ(P ′ (t), P (t), Q ′ (t));t = t + 1; 8 end</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Evolution of the Distribution Population</head><p>In order to better explore the distribution space, DEA-PPM carries out orthogonal exploration for individuals in Q(t). Algorithm 3 gives the flow of orthogonal exploration, which aims to change m worst individuals in Q by orthogonal transformation performed on c columns of a distribution matrix. Here, m is a random integer in [1, np/2] and c is a random integer in <ref type="bibr">[1, n/10]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">Algorithm 3: Q ′ = OrthExpQ(Q, P ) Input: Q, P ; Output: Q ′ ; 1 sorting Q by fitness values of corresponding individuals of Q; 2 take Qw as the collection of m worst individuals of Q; 3 Q ′ = Q \ Qw; 4 for q ∈ Qw do 5 q ′ ← q;</formula><p>6 randomly select c columns q ′ j l (l = 1, . . . , c) from q ′ ; 7 for l=1,. . . ,c do 8 generate a random orthogonal matrix M l ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">9 q ′ jl = M l q ′ jl ; 10 end 11 Q ′ = Q ′ ∪ q ′ 12 end</formula><p>In Algorithm 4, the intermediate distribution population Q ′ (t) is further updated to get Q(t). Given q [i] ∈ Q ′ (t), it is updated using v ′[i] and v [i] , two orientation combinations selected from P ′ and P , respectively. Columns of q [i]  are updated using either a exploitation strategy or a disturbance strategy presented as follows.</p><p>The exploitation strategy: To update the j th column of q [i] , it is first renewed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">r [i] l,j =    α 0 + (1 -α 0 )(q [i] l,j ) 2 , if l = v [i] j (1 -α 0 )(q [i] l,j ) 2 , if l = v [i] j l = 1, . . . , 4,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where v</p><p>[i] j is the j th component of v [i] . Then, an local orthogonal transformation is performed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">r [i] l1,j r [i] l2,j = U (∆θ j ) × r [i] l1,j r [i] l2,j ,<label>(16)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">l 1 = v ′[i] j , l 2 = v [i]</formula><p>j . U (∆θ j ) is an orthogonal matrix given by U (∆θ j ) = cos(∆θ j )sin(∆θ j ) sin(∆θ j ) cos(∆θ j ) .</p><p>Algorithm 4:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">Q ′ = Ref ineQ(P ′ , P , Q ′ ) Input: P ′ , P , Q ′ ; Output: Q; 1 for i = 1, . . . , np do 2 q [i] ∈ Q ′ , v ′[i] ∈ P ′ , v [i] ∈ P ; 3 for j=1,. . . ,n do 4 set rndj ∼ U (0, 1); 5 if rndj ≤ p0 then 6 r [i]</formula><p>j is generated by the exploitation strategy (Eqs. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">15</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_22">16</ref>));</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">7 else 8 r [i]</formula><p>j is generated by the disturbance strategy (Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_27">17</ref>));</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">9 end 10 end 11 r [i] = ( r [i] 1 , . . . , r [i] n ); 12 end</formula><p>The disturbance strategy: In order to prevent the distribution population from premature, the disturbance strategy is performed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">r [i] l,j =        λ(q [i] l 0 ,j ) 2 1-(1-λ)(q [i] l 0 ,j ) 2 , if l = l 0 (q [i] l,j ) 2 1-(1-λ)(q [i] l 0 ,j ) 2 , if l = l 0<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">l 0 = v [i] j .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Optimization of the Floorplan with a Fixed Outline</head><p>The floorplan is represented by the orientation vector r and the coordinate vectors x and y. In FFA-CD, the evolution of orientation vectors is implemented by iteration of solution population P (t), and the corresponding coordinate vectors are optimized by the function UpdateXY.</p><p>Initialization of the module orientation According to the principle of DEA-PPM, the solution population P ′ (t) is obtained by sampling the distribution population Q ′ (t). To accelerate the convergence process, the sampling process is performed with inheritance as the process illustrated in Algorithm 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Optimization of module position</head><p>With the orientation of modules confirmed by the solution population, the position of the modules is optimized by Algorithm 6. For a combination of position vector (x [i] , y [i] ), the global floorplanning is first implemented by optimizing f ; then, the weights of the constraint items is increased to legalize the floorplan approach by lines 4-7, or the legalization Algorithm 5: P ′ = SampleP (Q, P )</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">Input: Q, P ; Output: P ′ ; 1 for i = 1, . . . , np do 2 q [i] ∈ Q, v [i] ∈ P ; 3 for j=1,. . . ,n do 4 set rndj ∼ U (0, 1); 5 if rndj ≤ r then 6 sampling q [i] j to get v ′[i] j ; 7 else 8 v ′[i] j = v [i] j ; 9 end 10 end 11 v ′[i] = ( v ′[i] 1 , . . . , v ′[i] n ); 12 end 13 P ′ = np i=1 v ′[i]</formula><p>process is implemented by lines 9-10. The legalization process based on constraint graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> are implemented Graph(), which is presented in Algorithm 7. To prevent X and Y from falling into inferior local solutions, the coordinates are reinitialized if no better solution is obtained for several times. The legalization of Algorithm 7 is implemented as follows. Let (x ′ i , y ′ i ) be the lower-left coordinate of block v i . v i is to the left of v j if it holds</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">O i,j (y) &gt; 0, O i,j (x) = 0, x ′ i &lt; x ′ j ; v i is to the below of v j if O i,j (x) &gt; 0, O i,j (y) = 0, y ′ i &lt; y ′ j .</formula><p>Denote I i and J i as the left-module set and the lower-module set of module i, respectively. Then, the x-and y-coordinates of module i are updated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">x ′ i = max ∀vj ∈Ii (x ′ j + w j ), if I i = ∅ 0, otherwise;<label>(18)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_32">y ′ i = max ∀vj∈Ji (y ′ j + h j ), if J i = ∅ 0, otherwise. (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_33">)</formula><p>4 The Floorplanning Algorithm Based on the Golden Section Strategy</p><p>While the analytical optimization method is applied to the floorplanning problem without fixed-outline, it is a challenging task to minimize the floorplan area. In Algorithm 6: (P (t), X, Y , s) = U pdateXY (P ′ (t), X, Y , s)</p><p>Input: X, Y , s; Output: X, Y , s; this paper, we proposed a floorplanning algorithm based on the golden section strategy (FA-GSS), where minimization of the floorplan area is achieved by consecutively narrowing the contour of fixed outline.</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">1 for i = 1, . . . , np do 2 (x [i] , y [i] ) = CSA(f, (x [i] , y [i] ), kmax, s); 3 if d0 &gt; δ1 then 4 λ=min(1.5λ, λ + 30); 5 if c0 &gt; δ2 then 6 µ=min(1.1µ, µ + 10); 7 end 8 else 9 (x [i] , y [i] ) = CSA( f , (x [i] , y [i] ), 1000, max(s/2, 50)); 10 (x [i] , y [i] ) = Graph(x [i] , y [i] );</formula><p>Minimization of the floorplan area S(x, y, r) is equivalent to minimizing the blank ratio</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">γ = S(x, y, r) -A A * 100%, (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">)</formula><p>where A is the sum of areas of all modules. As presented in Algorithm 8, we use the golden section strategy to continuously reduce the area of the fixed contour. Given the initial white rate γ max and γ min , where the fixed-outline floorplanning is feasible for γ max but infeasible for γ min , we set</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">γ m = 0.618 * (γ max -γ min ) + γ min .</formula><p>If a legal layout can be obtained for γ m , then γ max =γ m ; otherwise, we set γ min =γ m . Repeat the section process until γ maxγ min &lt; ǫ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Experimental Results and Analysis</head><p>To verify the performance of the proposed algorithm, we conducted experiments on the well-known test benchmark GSRC. For all test circuits, the I/O pads are fixed at the given coordinates, and the modules of all circuits are hard modules.</p><p>All experiments are developed in C++ programming language program, and run in Microsoft Windows 10 on a laptop equipped with the AMD Ryzen 7 5800H @ 3.2GHz and 16GB system memory.</p><p>Algorithm 7: (x * , y * ) = Graph(x, y)</p><p>Input: (x, y); Output: (x * , y * ); 1 Sorting all modules according to the x-coordinates of the bottom-left corner and denote them as {v1, v2, . . . , vn}; 2 for i ← 1 to n do 3 update x ′ i and x * according to formula (18); 4 end 5 Sorting all modules according to the y-coordinates of the bottom-left corner and denote them as {v1, v2, . . . , vn}; 6 for i ← 1 to n do 7 update y ′ i and y * according to formula (19); 8 end</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Wirelength Optimization with Fixed-outline Constraints</head><p>We first test the performance of FFA-CD on the fixed-outline cases. It is compared with the well-known open source layout planner Parquet-4.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, where the floorplan is represented by the B*-tree and the simulated annealing algorithm to solve the combinatorial optimization model of floorplanning.</p><p>According to the given aspect ratio R, the width W * and height H * of the fixed contour are calculated as <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_38">W * = (1 + γ)A/R, H * = (1 + γ)AR,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>where A is the summed area of all modules, and γ is the white rate defined in (20). The experiment set the white rate as γ = 15%, the aspect ratio R as 1, 1.5, 2, and the population number as 5. For different aspect ratios, each experiment was independently run 10 times, and the results were shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Numerical results demonstrate that FFA-CD outperforms Parquet-4.5 on cases with more than 50 modules, but runs a bit slow for some of the small cases, which is attributed to the compact floorplan of Parquet-4.5. The combinatorial floorplan implemented by Parquet-4.5 could lead to smaller HPWL and shorter runtime, but its performance would degrade significantly while the problem size increases. The iteration mechanism based on CSA ensures that FFA-CD can explore the floorplan space more efficiently. At the same time, DEA-PPM is introduced to explore the rotation strategy, which increases the flexibility of the floorplan and greatly improves the success rate of small-scale problems. Consequently, the success rate of FF-CD was better than or equal to Parquet-4.5 for all cases. Meanwhile, better results on wirelength and tuntime is obtained in several different aspect ratios for the larger-scale cases (n50-n100).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Minimization of Wirelength and Area without Fixed-outline Constraints</head><p>For layout planning problems without fixed contour constraints, FA-GSS is used to optimize the wirelength and area. The proposed FA-GSS is compared with Algorithm 8: FA-GSS Input: f (x, y, r), f (x, y), r.</p><p>Output: Optimal solution (x * , y * ) and corresponding rotation strategy r * . 1 initialize Q(0) according to formula <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, and sample to generate P (0); 2 initialize X and Y , step control parameter s; 3 set the best solution in P (0) is p * , the corresponding distribution matrix is q * , and the module coordinates are (x * , y * ); 4 λ0 ← 1, µ0 ← 10, kmax ← 50, t ← 1; 5 initialize the maximum whitespace ratio γmax and minimum whitespace ratio γ min ; 6 while γmax -γ min &lt; ǫ do </p><formula xml:id="formula_39">Q ′ (t) = OrthExpQ(Q(t -1), P (t -1)); 11 P ′ (t) = SampleP (Q(t), P (t -1)); 12 (P (t), X, Y , s) = U pdateXY (P ′ (t), X, Y , s); 13 Q(t) = Ref ineQ(P ′ (t), P (t), Q ′ (t));<label>14</label></formula><p>Let's take the best solution for the current X, Y , and call it x ′ , y ′ ;</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">15 t = t + 1, update p * , q * , (x * , y * ), kmax = 35; 16 end 17 if f (x ′ , y ′ ) = 0 then</formula><p>18 γmax=γm; 19 else 20 γ min =γm; 21 end 22 end</p><p>Parquet-4.5 and the Hybrid Simulated Annealing Algorithm (HSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, where the population size is set as 5, and we get ǫ = 0.2%. Due to the different magnitude of wirelength and area, the cost function to minimized for the floorplanning problem without fixed outline is taken as</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">Cost = 0.5 * W W min + 0.5 * S S min ,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where W min and S min are the minimum values of W and A, respectively. The results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> show that all examples obtain better wirelength and shorter time when the aspect ratio is 1. So, we take R = 1 in FA-GSS for all test cases. For benchmarks in GSRC, the average Cost, and runtime (CPU) of ten independent runs are collected in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>.</p><p>The experimental results show that FA-GSS outperforms both Parquet-4.5 and HAS except for the n30 case. Although FA-GSS runs a bit slower than Parquet-4.5 when they are tested by the n30 case, FA-GSS has the smallest rate of increase in run time as the module size increases. This means that FA-GSS is expected to achieve excellent results on larger circuits. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, we formulate the flooplanning problem of VLSI as a mixed-variable optimization problem, where the discrete variables represent module orientations and the coordinates of modules are incorporated by continuous variables. Then, the DEA-PPM is introduced to get the module orientation, and coordinate variables are optimized by the CSA. Experimental results show that the proposed FFA-CD and FA-GSS, respectively developed for floorplanning problems with and without fixed-outline, can generally outperforms the floorplanning algorithms designed based on the B*-tree and the simulated annealing. Attributed to their low time complexity, the proposed algorithms are expected to address large-scale floorplanning problems effectively.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>11 end 12</head><label>1112</label><figDesc>end 13 s = max(0.95 * s, s min ); 14 if no better solution is obtained for several times then 15 reinitialize X, Y ; 16 end</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>7 α ← 1 ,</head><label>71</label><figDesc>λ ← 20, µ ← 100, γm = 0.618 * (γmax -γ min ) + γ min ; 8 calculate the width W * and height H * of the fixed profile; 9 while termination-condition 2 is not satisfied do 10</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>This research was partially supported by the National Key R&amp; D Program of China (No.2021ZD0114600) and the Guiding Project of Scientific Research Plan of Hubei Provincial Department of Education (No. B2022394).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Performance comparison for the fixed-outline cases of GSRC test problems.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">GSRC R</cell><cell>Parquet-4.5</cell><cell></cell><cell>FFA-CD</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">SR(%) HPWL CPU(s) SR(%) HPWL CPU(s)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 60 55603 0.04</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>55774</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>n10</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 60 55824 0.04</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>56696</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2.0 80</cell><cell>58247 0.04</cell><cell>90</cell><cell cols="2">58236 0.31</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 100 172173 0.28</cell><cell cols="3">100 160208 0.41</cell></row><row><cell>n30</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 90 173657 0.34</cell><cell cols="3">100 164237 0.28</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2.0 100 174568 0.32</cell><cell cols="3">100 166133 0.54</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 100 209343 0.68</cell><cell cols="3">100 185793 0.55</cell></row><row><cell>n50</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 100 211591 0.79</cell><cell cols="3">100 189878 0.41</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2.0 100 208311 0.78</cell><cell cols="3">100 195398 0.71</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 100 334719 2.10</cell><cell cols="3">100 293578 0.89</cell></row><row><cell>n100</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 100 340561 2.26</cell><cell cols="3">100 300079 1.05</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2.0 100 347708 2.26</cell><cell cols="3">100 308811 1.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 100 620097 9.03</cell><cell cols="3">100 521140 2.38</cell></row><row><cell>n200</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 100 625069 9.07</cell><cell cols="3">100 529918 2.53</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2.0 100 649728 9.24</cell><cell cols="3">100 541565 2.71</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.0 100 768747 19.08</cell><cell cols="3">100 588118 3.73</cell></row><row><cell>n300</cell><cell cols="2">1.5 100 787527 19.16</cell><cell cols="3">100 606548 3.85</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2.0 100 847588 19.63</cell><cell cols="3">100 626658 4.21</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Performance comparison for the GSRC test problems without fixedoutline constraints. Cost CPU(s) Cost CPU(s) n10 1.0885 0.03 1.0799 0.11 1.0688 0.17 n30 1.1040 0.19 1.0881 0.86 1.0959 0.69 n50 1.0871 0.47 1.0797 2.15 1.0750 1.29 n100 1.1034 1.61 1.1040 7.94 1.0648 3.53 n200 1.1301 6.23 1.1628 37.7 1.0713 8.96 n300 1.1765 12.87 1.2054 78.21 1.0715 15.13</figDesc><table><row><cell>GSRC</cell><cell>Parquet-4.5</cell><cell>HAS</cell><cell>FA-GSS</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cost CPU(s)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel multicriteria optimization technique for VLSI floorplanning based on hybridized firefly and ant colony systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Venkatesan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aljafari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Access</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14677" to="14692" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A modified multi-objective simulated annealing algorithm for fixed-outline floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Weng</forename><surname>Yifan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Zhen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Jianli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc of 2018 IEEE International Conference on Automation, Electronics and Electrical Engineering</title>
		<meeting>of 2018 IEEE International Conference on Automation, Electronics and Electrical Engineering<address><addrLine>Shenyang</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="39" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>AU-TEEE</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hybrid genetic algorithm for VLSI floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Jianli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zhu</forename><surname>Wenxing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc of 2010 IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Computing and Intelligent Systems</title>
		<meeting>of 2010 IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Computing and Intelligent Systems<address><addrLine>Xiamen</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="132" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A stable fixed-outline floorplanning algorithm for soft module</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Du</forename><surname>Shimin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xia</forename><surname>Yinshui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chu</forename><surname>Zhufei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Electronics &amp; Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1258" to="1265" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A modified simulated annealing algorithm and an excessive area model for floorplanning using fixed-outline constraints</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><surname>Zou Dexuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pan</forename><surname>Gai-Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers of Information Technology &amp; Electronic Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1228" to="1244" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel method on discrete particle swarm optimization for fixed-outline floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ye</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yin</forename><surname>Xi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Zhenyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc of 2020 IEEE International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Information Systems (ICAIIS)</title>
		<meeting>of 2020 IEEE International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Information Systems (ICAIIS)<address><addrLine>Dalian</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="595" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defer: deferred decision making enabled fixed-outline floorplanning algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J Z</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chu</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A quasi-newton-based floorplanner for fixedoutline floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ji</forename><surname>Pengli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">He</forename><surname>Kun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><surname>Zhengli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105225</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UFO: unified convex optimization algorithms for fixed-outline floorplanning considering pre-placed modules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hung Z X</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1034" to="1044" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization models and algorithms for placement of very large scale integrated circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Huang Zhipeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zhu</forename><surname>Xingquan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wenxing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations Research Transactions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PeF: poisson&apos;s equation based largescale fixed-outline floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Ximeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peng</forename><surname>Keyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Huang</forename><surname>Fuxing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2002" to="2015" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Handling orientation and aspect ratio of modules in electrostatics-based large scale fixed-outline floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 2023 IEEE/ACM International Conference on Computer Aided Design (ICCAD)</title>
		<meeting>of 2023 IEEE/ACM International Conference on Computer Aided Design (ICCAD)<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonsmooth optimization method for VLSI global placement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zhu</forename><surname>Wenxing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Jianli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peng</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="642" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey on estimation of distribution algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shude</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zengqi</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Automatica Sinica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distribution evolutionary algorithm for the graph coloring problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yongjian</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Huabin</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ning</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Swarm and Evolutionary Computation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-adaptive gaussian keyhole imaging butterfly optimization algorithm based on latin hypercube sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Xujie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Haiyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zhao Jinjin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Application Research of Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2751</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Min-cut floorplacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J A</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Adya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Papa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1313" to="1326" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved simulated annealing algorithm and area model for the fixed-outline floorplanning with hard modules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hao</forename><surname>Zou Dexuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pan</forename><surname>Guosheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">InL Proc of 2015 3rd International Symposium on Computational and Business Intelligence (ISCBI)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bali</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hybrid simulated annealing algorithm for nonslicing VLSI floorplanning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Jianli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zhu</forename><surname>Wenxing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ali</forename><forename type="middle">M M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, Part C (Applications and Reviews)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="544" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
